故事发生在凌家沟
This is the valley of Ling...
1937年初夏
as it was in the early summer of 1937.
凌家沟里世世代代住的都是农民
The people who lived here were farmers.
他们听说 在山的另一头还有另外一个不同的世界
They'd heard there was a world beyond, the hills that bounded their little valley...
但是从来没有人翻过山去看一下
... but as yet, no one had climbed those hills to see for himself.
这可能是因为他们比大多人都要知足的原因吧
Perhaps it is because they were more fortunate than most.
这里物产富饶 人们衣食无忧
The land was rich, and their bellies were full.
在这片土地上 生活着凌谭一家
On this farm, lived Ling Tan and his family.
他们是村里最幸福的一家人
And they were among the most fortunate.
既不是太富有 也不是太穷
They were neither too wealthy, nor too poor.
乡邻们都很敬重他们
And they were greatly respected in the nearby village.
他们住在一个大宅子里
They owned a strong house...
世世代代都在同一片土地上耕耘
... and tilled the soil that belonged to their ancestors.
凌家人天性善良又有点坏脑筋 聪明又有点愚昧
They were both good and bad, both wise and foolish...
大多数时候浑身散发着这些农民气息
... and sometimes all these things at the same moment.
因此 他们家跟其他农民家庭相比几乎没什么两样
And therefore, they were very much like such families in any other land.
又到了每年播种的时候了
It was time for the rice seedlings to be planted...
此时 凌谭心里只惦记着一件事
... and Ling Tan was eager for but one thing:
那就是在天黑前
To finish as much of the work as could be done...
早点把活干完
... before the sun was gone from the sky.
虽然老凌家的大儿子和二儿子也在帮忙着许多活儿
But Ling's first and second sons were eager for many other things as well.
但是至少他们都还年轻力壮
For they were young.
喂!
Hey!
- 是你娘在喊我吗 - 是的 爹
- Is that your mother? - Yes, my father.
快过来 老头子 我有话跟你说
Come, old man. I want to speak to you.
太阳下山后 有的是时间听女人唠叨
Time enough to speak with women when the sun is gone.
我知道你听到了 你个老不死的
I know you hear me, you old turnip.
你俩兄弟别停下 接着把活儿干完啊
You two do not stop for anything until the field is done.
放心吧 爹
Ease your heart about that, Father.
啥事 老太婆 啥事这么着急
What is it, old woman? What is it?
你聋了吗 我要像牛叫一样你才听得到吗
You grow deaf? Must I bawl like an ox to make you hear?
地里还有活儿没干完呢 你把我叫回来做啥
There is work and you call me from the fields.
来 来 来
Come. Come.
你就别太辛苦了 还有儿子们呢
You work too hard and too long. You have sons to labor for you.
瞎说啥呢 我还干得动
What nonsense is this? I'm not yet so feeble.
你早就不年轻了 你要多休息
You're no longer young and you must not strain.
休息啥  我现在不是还年轻呢
I do not strain myself. I'm as much a man as I ever was.
来来来  洗洗你的脏脚
Come now. Wash your legs.
看这泥巴地 都把你这把老骨头累的不成样子了
The very weight of the mud can tire a man of your great age.
说起来 我们是时候该给家里添多个儿媳妇了
Well, perhaps a younger wife with a softer will might be added to a man's household.
别光说不练啊 老头子
Bring her on, old man.
那也得该找个人说说媒啊
I shall have someone to help me with my work.
估计还没说上媒 你就去见阎王爷了
And you shall be in your grave before your time.
瞎说八道 我会等到那一天的 不信你等着瞧
I think I would survive. I may try it to see.
还记得你右耳朵后面的牙印吗 老不死的
What of those teeth marks behind your right ear, old turnip?
哪能忘啊 很久以前被一只母老虎咬的
A hill tiger bit me. It was a long time ago.
是啊是啊 我就是那只母老虎
I was the hill tiger.
要怪就只能怪当初 有人把我当成了家猫
You made the mistake of treating me like a tame house cat.
小心我再咬你一次
It could happen again.
我可是一朝被虎咬 十年怕老婆啊
Not so long as the scars remain to remind me.
过来 跟我在这里坐会儿行不
Is it not good with me here?
行 行 行 不过呢 勤劳的男人是不应该偷懒的
Yes, it is, but a man with his juices still in him should not so indulge himself.
- 我看我还是回地里干活去吧 - 没你在 地里的农活一样做得完
- I should go back to the fields. - The field will be finished without you.
来这边 闲着没事做的话 就帮我把鸭子拔拔毛好拿去市场卖
Here. If you must be useful, help me prepare these ducks for market.
拔鸭毛 那是你们娘们的事情
Ducks. That is woman's work.
老天要是给女人这多活儿干 那也得给女人找多几个帮手啊
If heaven sends a woman too much work, heaven will also send help to do it.
老太婆 你想得美啊 你以为老天会跟你想到一块啊
How is it, old woman, that heaven's will and yours are always the same?
山里草长得多好 牛吃得多肥啊
The grass is good in the hills and the ox grows fat.
你这是在说牛肥啊 还是说三弟肥啊
Which is the ox and which is our brother?
三弟是在做梦吗
Is our brother dreaming?
不是 他整天都是这脸傻样
No, that vacant look is his usual expression.
你俩真脏啊 是不是刚在泥里打完滚啊
You are very dirty. Have you been playing in the mud?
是啊 玩得开心着呢 你明天要不要一起来打滚啊
We have. It was very pleasant. Why do you not join us tomorrow?
你要求太多了吧
Oh, you ask too much.
哪里有活干 哪里准看不到老三
Where you find hard work, you will not find our brother.
大家都有活儿干好不好 只是有人用力气干活 有人用脑子干活
There is work for all. For those with strong backs and for those with strong minds.
脑子聪明 就不用干你们的粗活
If the mind is strong,the back need not bend.
而且也不用把脚弄脏
Nor need the feet get muddy.
他哪里聪明啊 一肚子驴脾气
He has no mind, only a temper.
老二 这些日子你总是魂不守舍的 有啥烦心事啊
Brother, your mind is absent these days. Why is this?
我最近在想一些事情 都快烦死我了
I think, and my thoughts trouble me.
说出来 大哥给你想想办法
What is a brother for if not to share your troubles?
好吧 事情是这样的
Well, then, here is one of the things:
我发现 这个女人啊 跟我们男人很不一样啊
Women are not the same as we are.
老二啊 都结婚四个月 你才发现这个啊
Married four months and you just found this out?
还有还有呢 女人跟我们男人想的也不一样
But here is another thing: Women do not think as men do.
这女人哪里会想啊 她们脑袋里根本就想不出什么东西
Women should not think.They're not equal to it.
我觉得我家小玉就不一样
My wife Jade is equal to it.
你想太多了吧
You worry too much about that one of yours.
等以后她生了儿子 就会老老实实带孩子了
When she has a son, a son will be more important.
生儿子  我都结婚这么久了 都还没跟她洞房呢!
A son. I have not yet a wife... As I would have her.
她就像阵西北风一样 我一碰她 呼的一下就不见了
She is like a western wind. When I reach for her, she's gone.
西北风也可以驯服啊
Even western wind can be caught and tamed.
我可不想驯服她 我想多理解她
I do not want her tame.Only, I do not understand her.
虽然她的人是我的 但是感觉她的心还不是
She is mine and yet she is not mine.
每次我一碰她 她整个人就像丢了魂似的
When I touch her, it is as if her spirit goes and only her body is left.
她长得又好看 又好闻 你还不满足啊
She is beautiful and sweet-smelling. Is that not enough?
不过我反倒是觉得是你的问题 我偷偷观察过
It is your fault. I've watched you.
当我们这些大老爷们坐一起抽烟的时候 你总是第一个走开
When the men sit and smoke, you're the first to leave.
我犯困了而已啊 我能有什么办法啊
Can I help it if the desire for sleep overcomes me?
老弟啊 这个女人的温柔乡 可是会把男人变成软蛋的啊
Do you not know that with a woman, eagerness passes for weakness?
- 你看 大老爷们坐一起时我总是最后一个走 - 你说的容易
- Sit with the old men until the last as I do.  - That is easy for you.
而且 我发现小玉不会老呆在一个地方
I've not found Jade in the same place twice.
也从来不等我睡觉
And never waiting for me.
- 你觉得这就是问题的关键   - 是的
- Do you think that is the answer to the troubles?  - Yes.
天亮前我也碰不了她 天亮之后就更不用说
Then I will not go to her until dawn. And perhaps not even then.
小玉 小兰 你们老公回来了
Jade, Orchid. The men of the house are at home.
这儿媳妇们都跑哪里去了啊
Now, where are the women my sons married?
小玉 小兰 原来你们在这里啊
Jade, Orchid. Oh, there you are.
- 你家老公都回来了 去看看有什么需要帮忙的  - 好的 娘
- Your husband comes. Attend him.  - I go, Mother.
- 拿上我刚洗好的毛巾
- Take this clean towel I have made ready.
娘 我想跟你说说我的小女儿的事情
Mother, I must tell you about my youngest child.
小孙女 她怎么了
My grandchild? What about her?
她刚刚坐在那里 突然 张开了嘴 我在想...
She was lying there and all at once, she opened her mouth and I thought...
我在想 她是不是 要开口讲话了
I thought she was going to speak.
你啊 就是那些生过孩子
You are surely one of those who has given birth...
却还是满头死脑筋的人
...and remains in a daze at what you've done.
- 你老公等着呢 快去 - 好的
- Your husband waits. - Yes.
小玉啊
Jade.
小玉!
看着点!
你们要才看着点!
Take care.
You take care.
真希望你把那烦人的笛子给没收了
I wish you would take that squealing thing from him.
你也是时候给他找个老婆 他也该给家里添丁了
You should get him a wife. It's time he brought grandsons into this house.
不着急 不着急
即使你让他去讨个老婆
In time. In time.
If you told him to marry...
他也不一定会听你的话
...you're not sure he would obey.
- 所以你得帮他准备准备啊了  - 没那个必要吧
- So you spare yourself dealing with him. - There is no need to deal with him.
- 我还不清楚你心里想什么吗  - 你倒说说看
- Shall I tell you a secret thing in your heart? - No.
你最疼爱小儿子 但这事不好办
Our third son is the son you love best, but most uneasily.
他脾气跟老大老二不一样 你就怕这个
He's different from the others. You fear that.
所以你一直不敢给他找老婆
That's why you go on the far side of an argument.
儿子们要毛巾了
Our sons wait for their towels.
小玉 我的毛巾呢  小玉
Jade. Jade, where is my towel? Jade?
谢谢 小玉
Thank you, Jade.
小玉 我中午就没看见你老婆小玉了
I've not seen her since the sun was in the middle of the sky.
估计我们被媒人骗了
The matchmaker cheated us.
- 啥 我老婆不在家  - 我就没找到她人
- What? My wife is not in the house?  - I could not find her.
这女人家啊 要是不裹脚了 就像羊儿一样到处乱跑
This comes of women having their feet free. Nowadays they run around like goats.
- 要我帮忙吗 娘 - 你自个儿的活儿做完了
- May I help you, Mother? - Have you ever done so?
还是说 做了等于白做
Or has your worthless one?
家里那堆家务活 我刚都已经通通做完了
All that is done in this house, I do.
至少你们大嫂在家呆着的时候 小玉才有借口去村里玩
At least my wife stays at home. Jade has a reason to go to the village.
这男人要是一发话啊 女人就得随叫随到
When a woman knows a man wants her, she will ever display herself.
- 你说得对 - 你难道还没发现四表哥对小玉还余情未了吗
- That is true. - Have you not seen our fourth cousin look at Jade?
他就像只病猫一样盯着
He resembles a sick cat.
她要是我老婆 我准揍到她丑得没脸见人
I would beat her until she was not so good to look upon.
这女人啊 越打越听话
If more of that were done, there will be less trouble with wives.
你们爷们可要有点真能耐才行
Only men should make sure first they are able.
现在的新女性可是打不得的
These new-fashioned women are not easily beaten.
我这就穿衣服去找她 让你们瞧瞧什么叫真能耐
I will dress and go find her.Then we will see who is able.
还是先吃饱饭吧 儿子 吃饱了才有能耐打老婆
Eat first, my son, and your arm will be stronger for all this beating.
谁躲在屋外偷看呢
Who tries to see within our house without himself being seen?
吃好了没有 三表婶
Are you eating, wife of my third cousin?
我们吃得不是那么好啊 你看看 连肉都没有
Our rice is poor and scanty.And we have no pork at all.
- 你要不要也一起吃点  - 不了 不了 谢谢
- But will you share it with us? - Thank you. But I cannot.
你一个人在家吗 四表哥在吗
Are you alone, then? Is my fourth cousin not here?
我儿子还没回来呢
My son is not home yet.
不过你三表伯在家
But your third cousin, my honored husband, is here.
你好 三表伯 你在书里又发现什么新东西了
How are you, sir? What new thing have you found in your book?
狗屁新东西 他读书都读到到家里揭不开锅了
Nothing his family can chew, swallow and grow fat on, I can tell you.
四表哥还在城里吗
My fourth cousin is in the city perhaps?
不知道 我儿子吃了午饭就不见了
I do not know. My son has been gone since the noon meal.
哦 那我先走了 我在村里还有点事
Well, I must get on. I have business in the village.
满口屁话
He lies.
都这个点了 村里能有啥事呢
He has no business in the village at this hour.
一定是找他们家老婆小玉去了
He looks for his wife, Jade.
要是他发现小玉和我儿子在一起 会不会....
And if he finds her with our son, as he well may...
小玉早都嫁给老二了 而且我儿子早就死心了
Jade is married to Lao Er. The thing my son felt for her has ended.
除非他们凌家都死光了 不然这事没完
It will never be ended until one of them is dead.
说来说去都是你的错 老书呆子 都是你 害的我们吃不饱
You old book fool, it is your fault. It is your fault we starve.
都是因为你 我们家儿子才娶不到小玉
It is your fault we did not get Jade for our son.
- 这女人家的事与我何干啊  - 女人家
- Can I control a woman's choice? - A woman's choice?
难道不是因为你收了你表弟凌谭30个大洋
Did not your cousin Ling Tan give you 30 silver dollars?
难道不是你不让你家儿子娶小玉吗
Did you not tell our son he could not have the girl?
闭嘴 老婆子 我在看书呢
Quiet, woman. I read.
就是因为这样 老凌家一定会遭报应的
Out of all this, something terrible will happen.
我们是城里的大学生 今天...
We are students who have come from the university...
到这里是来告诉乡亲们
...to travel through the country and tell you and others like you...
北方发生战乱了
...news of the war in the North.
日本鬼子正向我们逼近
The Japanese march toward us.
这两张图告诉我们 日本鬼子侵略我们国家 还都在...
These are two pictures of what the Japanese are doing.
干些什么勾当
They are doing it now.
当你们坐在这里看的时候 这些悲剧正在别的地方发生
While you sit here and watch, these very things are happening.
老沈 看到我四表哥了没
Shen, have you seen my fourth cousin?
我们的同胞正惨遭杀戮 他们的尸骨正被无情掩埋
These are your people they are murdering and mine.
我们的国家正在被野蛮地侵略
This is our country they are looting.
敌人惨无人道 他们把我们当奴隶一样
The enemy is ruthless. He regards us only as slaves.
我们不能妥协 我们要学会反抗
We cannot deal with him. We must resist him.
- 不好意思 - 在找人么
- I'm sorry. - Seeking someone perhaps?
- 不是你边上的这位  - 我说 如果小玉是我老婆...
- Not the one who would sit near you.  - If she were my wife...
她要是离开你 我会替她高兴的
It is with pleasure that I leave you.
当日本鬼子来到你们的村子
When the Japanese reach your village...
他们会甜言蜜语欺骗你们 然后用双手沾满你们的鲜血
...they will come with lies in their mouths and death in their hands.
你们必须反抗他们 宁死不屈
And you must resist them, even to your own deaths.
坚持到底
And beyond.
你们会这样做吗
Are you able to do this?
告诉我你们能做到 你们站起来告诉我 你们会这样做
Tell me you are. All of you rise and tell me you are able.
我们会
We are able.
看到没 难道只有一个人吗
See? There is one who speaks.
还有没有其他人吗 来 告诉我
Are there not others? Tell me. Come.
来吧 乡亲们
Yes. Come.
你去吧 我饿了
You come. I'm hungry.
女人就应该给家里的男人做饭
The woman should have food ready when her man is hungry.
我老婆现在就老老实实呆在家里呢
My wife is at home where she should be.
难道我这是在对牛弹琴吗
Am I speaking into the wind?
你们难道对自己的所见所闻都无动于衷吗
Have you not understood what you have seen and heard?
我知道你们会起来反抗敌人的
I know you have. Tell me you will resist the enemy when he comes.
- 怎么反抗 小伙子 - 难道赤手空拳去跟机器打啊
- How then can we resist?  - Can we fight machines with our hands?
你为什么总是这样抛头露面 在大伙儿面前丢我的脸
Why do you shame me by showing yourself off to everybody?
我刚到家的时候 肚子都饿得咕咕叫了
I come home, my belly roaring like a hungry lion.
那你怎么不自个儿弄点吃的啊
Why did you not eat and silence it?
-你都不在家 我怎么吃得下 -我在爹娘面前一个人吃饭多不好
- How can I when you're not in your place? - I'm ashamed before my parents.
- 真希望你不会一个人上街 - 为什么
- I wish you'd not go in the street alone. - Why?
- 其他男人会看到你的 - 我又不看他们
- Other men will see you.  - I do not look.
我是不想让他们看到你而已!你可是我的老婆
I do not want them to look at you. You're my wife.
但是我不可能一直躲在院子里不出门吧 这又不是旧社会
But I cannot stay always in the courtyard.These are not ancient times.
我倒是希望这是旧社会 这样我就可以把你锁起来
I wish it were those times. I'd like to lock you up.
你要是把我锁起来 那我宁可饿死
If you lock me up,I wouldn't eat and then die.
我才舍不得让你饿死
I would not let you.
现在是新社会了 我想来就来 想走就走
But these are the new times, and I will come and go as I please.
- 真想扇你一巴掌 - 我又没做错事!
- I should beat you. - I have done nothing.
你不守妇道
But you are not where a woman should be at...
你就应该在家相夫教子
At home, waiting for her husband.
我还想问你一件事
And there is this thing.
在我们结婚前 那时候你还有的选择
Before we were wed, when the choice was put to you...
为什么选了我 而没有选四表哥
...why did you not choose me above my fourth cousin?
如果现在让你选 你还会选我吗
If you could choose now,which would it be?
你们两个都不缺胳膊少腿
You both have two arms and legs, and all your fingers and toes.
也都不是瘌痢头 斗鸡眼
Neither of you are scabby-headed, nor cross-eyed.
- 选谁不都一样吗  - 你这话说的让我倒胃口
- What, then, is the difference between you? - You used me very ill.
不过你看起来又白又瘦 一副可怜巴巴的样子 活像贱骨头
You look so pale and so thin. You are so to be pitied, you big turnip.
我真希望我是个读书人
I wish I were a man of learning.
这样我就可以把心里的想法告诉你 你也就能知道我的感觉了
I wish I knew the words to ease myself so I could tell you what I feel.
你能有什么感觉
What do you feel?
我对你有感觉 但是...
I know, but...
但是我说不出来具体是什么样的感觉
I do not have the words.
我也不是个读书人
I too am not very learned.
难道就是因为这个原因你才不跟我说话吗
Is that why you do not often speak to me?
两个人只有多说话 才能相互理解
Two must speak for understanding.
如果我跟你诉说心中之事 你是否也愿意告诉我你的感受呢
If I tell you everything that is in me,will you tell me all that is in you?
愿意
那今晚我们一起聊聊
Yes.
Then tonight we will speak together?
好的
Yes.
帮我把吃的拿过来 我要在院子里吃
Fetch me my food. I will eat here in the courtyard.
- 好的 老公 - 还有啊 今天你都没做饭
- Yes, my husband.  - And since you did not cook the meal...
- 就帮忙打扫一下院子吧  - 好的 老公
- ...you may clean up after it. - Yes, my husband.
老二刚刚肯定揍她老婆了
He must have beaten her.
我可不是吹牛皮
I do not take too much credit to myself...
怎么说我也是村里唯一的读书人啊
...that I'm the only man in these parts who can read and write.
但是如果你不给我弄口饭吃
But how would I find time for my books if you did not send me rice...
多给点肉啊添几件衣服什么的 我哪有时间读书啊
...and a new coat now and then,and sometimes even meat?
你是个受人尊敬的文化人 老表
You are a scholar and my honored cousin.
你想安逸一点生活 这也是应该的
It is only proper that your needs and comforts be supplied.
我这地里收成也够我们大伙吃的
My land yields enough for all.
小兰 孙子该睡觉了
Orchid, it is time my grandson was in his bed.
- 知道了 娘 - 但是老表啊 你是否想过
- Yes, my mother. - But, cousin, have you ever thought of this:
过几年你也会入土为安
When your time comes to go into the earth yourself...
你是不是得提前帮儿子们分好家产啊
...shall you divide your land between your sons?
对的 我也想过这件事
Yes, I have thought of that.
你得开个好头 大哥
别坏了祖宗的老规矩
You have made a good beginning.
Do not spoil it.
家产够不够他们分啊
Will there still be enough for all?
还是说他们会因为吃不饱饭 而大打出手呢
Or will they quarrel because their bellies are not fully
老大 你来说说 告诉表叔
As my eldest son, you must answer our cousin.
地里的收成够不够一家人吃饱肚子
Can this land feed three men and their wives and children after I am gone?
可以啊 我少吃点肉 如果弟弟们愿意 我也跟他们和睦相处啊
It can. For I will eat less meat, if my brothers will, and leave in peace with them.
你看 我教会了我儿子们和睦共处之道 这样我也知足了
If I have taught my sons that peace is good, I am content.
爹 如果你也跟我讲讲和睦之道的话 就不会这么早就知足了
If you had been with me today, you would not speak so easily of peace, my father.
你这么一说 要是我真的跟我儿媳妇讲道理的话
If it were proper for a man to speak to his daughter-in-law...
我倒是想问问 我们大老爷们讨论和睦之道有什么不妥呢
...l'd ask her why should not peaceful men speak of peace.
别怪小玉 爹 她是为今天茶馆里发生的事情而感到不安...
Forgive my wife, Father, for speaking so boldly, but today at the teahouse...
大学生们给村民们看了一些照片
...students came and showed the magic pictures and talked.
他们说北方战乱 东洋鬼子们
They told of the war in the North and how the dwarfs...
正对那里的人烧杀抢夺
...from the East Ocean islands burn cities and kill our people.
如果儿媳妇还记得的话 我倒是想起来了
I wonder if my daughter remembers...
以前这些大学生还给我们看过虫子的照片呢
-...when other students brought the pictures of flies.
我记得 跟牛一样大的虫子
I remember.Flies as large as water buffalo.
然后他们说 这些东西比老虎还可怕
Yes, and they told us they were more dangerous than tigers.
但是其实我们都知道
And everyone knows that our flies...
这些小虫子啊 根本没有什么危害
...are as small as a grain of rice and as harmless.
即使现在这些照片跟以往不一样 但是
And so does it not follow that today also perhaps...
学生们说的话实在是太夸张了
...both words and pictures were made
too large to be either truth or life?
我这么一说 是不是可以打消我儿媳妇的顾虑呢
Does that not quiet the woman's fear of my daughter?
那是肯定的 快去睡觉吧 小玉
Of course it does.And it is time she was in her bed.
但是我们确实知道北方发生的那些杀人放火的事情
But we who are men know that there is killing and suffering in the North.
你觉得战乱会牵扯到我们吗 爹
And do you not believe it will come here, Father?
我倒是觉得
I believe something else.
如果一个人安分守己
If a man lives his life in decency and as he should...
就算什么邪魔外道来了 也动不了他半根汗毛
...and then evil comes to him, it cannot harm him.
因为他总有办法可以扛过去 这就是我的生存之道
And he can conquer and overcome it. This, I live by.
也是乡亲们的生存之道
And so I think do all the kinsmen in our village.
- 我们都是老实人 - 对对对
- We are men of peace. - True, true, true.
何况北方离这里远着呢 更不用说我的热炕头了 我也得赶紧上去睡觉了
Also, the North is a long way from here. And so is my bed, and I must get to it.
她估计心里还憋屈呢 你默数个五百下 等她消气了再去找她
She still is not cured. Wait 500 heartbeats. Then go to her.
我晚上刚出门的时候 月亮都照出我的影子呢
I will have my shadow to walk home with.
是啊 今天的月亮又大又圆的
Yes, the moon is round tonight and the color of a ripe peach.
我从书里读到说 地球也是圆的
I have read that the Earth, too, is round.
你上次跟我说过这件事情 不过我就纳闷
You have told me that but one thing troubles me.
既然这地球是圆的 那人怎么站在上面呢
How is it then if the world is round that men on the bottom side can walk?
那书上的事情都乱套了
Everything is opposite there.
小孩子一生出来是白头发 蓝眼睛
Children are born with white hair and blue eyes.
还有书都是反过来印 倒过来读的...
Scholars begin to the write from the wrong side of the page...
那些年轻娃子居然比老一辈还受欢迎
...and youth is admired instead of age.
按这样一来 他们要是走路头朝下 我也不觉得奇怪了
So why can we not believe they walk with their heads hanging down?
真笑死人了
And enjoy it too.
老太婆 你有没有想过 在这地的另外一边
Old woman, have you ever thought that somewhere very far below...
离我们这里十万八千里的地方
...the spot where we stand, our land goes on and on...
有个陌生人站在那里
...until at last a stranger stands on it?
他也在那地里头 播种收割么
And plants seed and takes his harvest from it as though it were his own?
这地儿现在可是我们家的 还是我们儿子的
But it is not. It is ours. And our sons' after us.
是啊是啊 这地里的每一分每一寸都是我们的
Yes, the land is ours as deep as it goes beneath our feet.
我们头上的星星也是属于我们的 他们头上的才是他们的
And the stars above our heads belong to us, and whatever there is beyond them.
但是我还是觉得那地里的陌生人比较烦
But I'm troubled about that stranger on our land.
说不定他偷偷割我们的小麦呢
Somewhere he reaps his grain without telling you.
- 我觉得你应该收他的租 - 对哦 是应该收租
- You should ask him for rent. - That I would do.
我得跟他约法三章啊
I would have the law on him if I knew how to tell him so.
嘿 别烦了 老二 打女人总会有好处的
Do not be troubled, my son.It is often good to beat a woman.
哦 哦 是的 娘
Oh, yes. Yes, my mother.
老头子 还有件事情我有点担心
Old man, there is something here and now that troubles me.
是关于小玉的
It is Jade.
小兰虽然有点傻 但是也听我的话
Orchid is stupid but she does what I tell her to do.
这个小玉呢   我就不怎么喜欢她
While Jade...I do not think I like her.
你知道为什么吗 因为她跟你年轻时候一模一样
Do you know why? Because she is the same as you are yourself.
女人心海底针啊 我告诉你啊
No man can tell what will come out of her.And here is another thing:
我们家老二可不会嫌弃她 就像我当年也不会嫌弃你一样
Our second son will never tire of her as I have never tired of you.
今天可是头一回 你舍得等我
This is the first time I found you waiting for me.
那谁先聊
Who will speak first, then?
你先 你想知道我什么
You. Ask me what you will.
那个
Well, then...
你最近老在想什么事情
What are you thinking all day?
我想很多事情 同时想二三十件事情
I think 20 and 30 things at a time.
我的脑子根本停不下来 就像上了发条的机器一样
My thoughts are like a chain,and one is fast to the other.
- 那是关于什么的 - 我在想鸟为什么会飞
- But what are they? - I think of the bird and how it flies.
我怎么就不能也从地上飞起来
And why is it I cannot lift myself above the earth.
那现在呢 现在你在想什么
But now, what are you thinking now?
现在
Now?
啥都不想
I think nothing.
哦 那...
Well, then...
那么第一次你看到我的,你又在想些什么呢
...what did you think of me the first time you saw me?
我还真记不起来了
我是说....
I cannot remember.
No, I mean... I mean...
我们结婚之 后
...after we were married.
我看到你比我长得高 觉得很高兴 因为我也是个大高个
I was glad you were taller than I.For a woman, I am too tall.
你不高 然后你当时还想些什么呢
No, you are not. Then what did you think?
然后我在想 你会怎么看我
And then I wondered what you thought of me.
你知道我想要你的啊
But you knew that I wanted you.
- 然后 我再想... - 想啥
- And then I wondered... - Yes?
我再想你会不会给我我要的东西
I wondered if you would give me the thing I would have.
告诉我什么东西 我去买给你
Tell me. I will buy it for you.
买
Buy?
我要的东西估计你都买不到
Perhaps all the things I want cannot be bought.
女人不都喜欢小礼物嘛 告诉我是什么
All women like presents. Tell me what it is.
我想要...
I want...
一对耳环
Earrings.
这个啊 一对耳环而已
Yes, that is it. A pair of earrings.
我明早就去给你买
I will buy them for you tomorrow.
- 这样你就开心啦 - 是吧
- Now have I made you happy?  - Yes.
等等 我还是不开心 我不想要耳环了
No. You have not made me happy. I do not want earrings.
但是肯定有什么东西我可以买来让你开心的啊
But there is something that can be bought that I would have.
- 那就给我一本书吧 - 一本书
- Buy me a book. - A book?
- 但是你不识字啊  - 我识字的
- But you cannot read. - I can read.
- 女人都不认识字的啊 - 我学过
- Women like you never read. - I learned.
我哥哥教过我 虽然每次也就一两个词
A word or two at a time. My brother could read and I learned from him.
每天也就那么一点点
A little every day.
不过我从来没有属于自己的书
But I have no book of my own.
我从来没看到我们家里有哪一个女人会读书的
I never thought to see a woman read in this house.
但是家庭主妇也得为了自己的生活而做出点改变啊
There must be changes even in a household if there is to be life and growth.
我也不清楚 其实像我爹我娘这样也没什么不好
I do not know that.My mother and my father have done well.
-但他们是老一代人 我们可是新时代人 - 我可搞不清自己是不是新时代人
- But they are of the old. We are of the new. - Oh, I am not sure if I am of the new.
不过我还是会给你买本书的
I will buy you the book.
- 你生气啦 - 哪有 我可舍不得生你的气
- You are angry? - There is no room in my mind for anger.
只不过...
It is...
这些事情我不是很了解你而已
It is just that I do not understand.
- 给你请安了 周先生  - 谢谢你
- Ten thousand greetings, Mr. Chow. - Thank you.
- 你还好吧 小伙子 - 还不错
- You are well, young sir? - Yes.
- 我想见见我姐夫吴连 - 他在里头呢 正在早休
- I would see my brother-in-law, Wu Lien.  - He is within. He takes his morning rest.
这屋里的人 都睡着了吗
Are all asleep in this house?
早安 姐夫 早安 老太太
I greet you, my brother-in-law. And your honored mother.
欢迎欢迎 快坐下
Welcome, welcome. Sit down.
孩子他娘 你二弟来了
Here's your second brother,mother of my children.
- 快坐快坐 - 谢谢
- Sit down, sit down. - Thanks.
你还是老样子啊 土里土气的
Well, then, you're a farmer and one who looks it.
指甲里面全是泥巴啊
The dirt is still beneath your fingernails.
二弟 家里老人跟其他人都还好吧
My brother, how are the old ones and all of the others?
- 都还好 你有心啦  - 来 快点告诉我
- Well, thank you. - Tell me...
是不是我弟妹怀孕了
...is my sister-in-law, Jade,with child yet?
你居然对小孩不感兴趣的啊
Can it be you take no interest?
谁像你啊 两个小孩你都不嫌烦
It would seem you take interest enough for both.
- 我再怎么烦 我二弟也还是当不了爹啊 - 你说的是
- My interest will never make him a father. - No.
我想你也饿了 我看得出来
But you are hungry. I can tell.
这城里的每个人都应该学我
In each generation, a city man should do as I have done.
娶个乡下老婆
Take for a wife a woman from the country.
这样生出来的小孩才能又结实又强壮
Thus the line...Thus the line is kept strong and hard.
是啊 看看这小孩跟你一样的聪明啊
And here is the proof of your wisdom.
姐夫
Brother-in-law?
你能不能帮我出一下主意
Will you dip into your wisdom and tell me a thing?
可以吗 我知道你是个读书人
Yeah? I know you're a man who reads.
是啊 是啊 我是读过几年书
Yes. Yes, I read.
不过大多数也只是在冬天取暖或者夏天乘凉的时候才翻翻
Often in the winter to warm my blood.Sometimes in the summer to cool it.
如果你想买本书 你会买什么书
If you were to buy a book,what book would it be?
书可是有好多种类的啊
Well, there are books for every need.
如果你是要那种玉女心经什么的书
If a man wishes to read secretly for his own private pleasure...
我现在手头倒是有几本
...there are books for that.
不是 那你究竟是要什么书啊
No? Well then,for what is your book wanted?
我娶了个老婆比较特别
I married my woman thinking her like any other one and...
她告诉我想要一本书看看
Now I find out she can read and wants a book.
这样啊
So.
孩子他娘 你也是个女人家
You're only a woman, mother of my children...
如果你会读书的话 你想读本什么样的书
...but if you could read, what would you like to read?
- 我压根就没想过这事 - 等等我想到一本了
- I never thought...  - I have thought of the one.
里面什么都有 里面说无论强弱 人都是有罪的
It has everything in it. The good prosper and the wicked are punished.
- 这个书的名字就叫做  - 我们都是兄弟姐妹
- The name of the book is  - All Men Are Brothers.
- 谢谢你 我会记住这个书名的 - 老板
- Thank you. I will remember what you... - Sir.
老板 老板 不好了
Sir. Sir, there is something.
- 又是上次那些大学生  - 这次比上次还糟糕 事儿闹大了 老板
- As before? - Worse than before. Much louder, sir.
他们说已经警告过你很多次了 他们现在没耐心了
They said they have warned you many times and their patience is at an end.
这帮黄毛学生只会惹是生非
These students cause trouble.
难道我一个老实生意人都没法过安稳日子了吗
An honest merchant cannot live in peace these times.
我说 怎么啦
Well, what is this?
我们再次警告你 别再跟日本鬼子做生意
We ask you once more, do not deal with the Japanese.
我们国家正在跟日本打仗 你不能一边卖日货 一边说自己爱国
We're at war. You cannot buy and sell Japanese goods and call yourself a patriot.
你们这么一说 还让不让人活了啊
Do you ask me to stop breathing in and out?
我这儿可是正经生意 有钱赚的你们懂不
There's a call for these, and a profit in them.
你们学生省点功夫 天下就太平了
Save your breath for arguments you can win.
那我们现在就让你不太平!
Then we must speak to you in words you can hear.
- 通通给我砸了 - 住手 你们这些强盗 住手
- Leave nothing. - Stop. You are vandals. Stop.
砸掉所有日货
Destroy all Japanese goods.
我们得让他知道自己的所作所为
We must make him understand what he has done.
强盗啊  小偷啊 你们会付出代价的 你们这些小偷
Bandits. Thieves.You'll pay for this. Thieves.
这是唯一可以让他明白的办法
This is the only way to make him see.
今天的事情 也会发生在任何跟日本人做生意的地方
What's happens here will happen to every shop that sells Japanese goods.
不 不
No. No.
吴连跟那些剥削你们血汗钱的人是一样的
Wu Lien walks hand in hand with those who deal in your blood.
我只是个生意人啊 为什么砸掉我的东西啊
I'm only a merchant. Why do you destroy my goods?
他做日本人的生意 日本鬼子用这些钱反过来杀害我们
He pays for Japanese goods in money that'll come back to us in pain and death.
没有没有 我只做清白生意啊 没有害人啊
No, no, I deal only in innocent things that harm no one.
这个吴连 爱钱胜过爱我们国家
This man, Wu Lien, loves his cash box above his country.
那不是真的 不是真的啊
That is not true. That's not true.
跟这种人划清界限吧 他跟日本鬼子没什么两样
Turn away from this traitor as you would turn from the Japanese.
走
Come.
你怎么能这么说呢
How can you say that?
这可是我毕生经营的生意啊
Can it be that the thing I have done all my life...
怎么现在我就成了个罪犯了呢
...is now held against me as a crime?
你看到没
Did you see...?
这些生意人现在都像躲着远远的
Did you see those merchants turn away from me as from a bad odor?
- 他们跟我没什么两样啊 - 想开点 姐夫 一切都会过去的
- They are of my own kind. - Be of stout heart, my brother. It will pass.
不不不 我可不这么认为 我又不傻
No, no, I do not think it will and I'm not a stupid man.
我得好好计划一下 不然以后这日子没法过了
I must turn this thing over in my mind.Decide what to do in the days I see ahead.
我得掂量一下该怎么做
I must think and weigh what comes out.
好好计划一下
And think again.
那个陌生青年跳下来 走的远远的
And then this strange young man jumped down, ran away and was gone.
- 他是强盗吗  - 不是 听说只是一个大学生而已
- Was he a bandit, then? - No, it was said he was a student.
你今天碰到这破事 然后还跑去买了本破书
First you encounter this trouble and then you buy a book.
小玉的那本书吧 叫什么名字来着
This book that Jade now has, what is it?
- 应该有书名的吧 - 是有的
- Books have names. - So has this one.
- 叫 我们都是兄弟姐妹  - 我们都是兄弟姐妹
- It is called All Men Are Brothers. - All Men Are Brothers?
那上次我们说的 那个站在我们地里头的陌生人
What of the stranger who lives on the other side of the earth...
偷割我们的小麦的那个 也是我们兄弟姐妹 我可不这么想
...and reaps his grain on my land? Is he my brother? I think not.
你们这么一说 我今天倒是看了一下地里 今年萝卜长得有点小
Today I pulled a turnip.They grow small this year.
我在想啊 会不会就是那个素不相识的兄弟干的好事呢
Can it be this strange brother is pulling at the roots to plague us?
我觉得就是那王八羔子干的
It's good to have him to blame.
一本书噢 小玉终于有书可以读了
A book. And Jade can read in it.
你看看 又动起新念头了吧 一本书啊
You see? An idea spreads. A book.
我得再说一遍 这种东西 给了女人可不是什么好事情
I have said and say again it is wrong to give a woman such a dangerous thing.
是不合理 我老婆是不可能有本书看的
It is unnatural and mine will never have one.
万一你老婆有了小孩呢 她如果没看完书的话 会有什么打算
What if a child comes? What will your woman do if she has not finished the book?
难道她可以一边看书 一边生小孩
Will she read on and let the child be born anyhow?
她自己应付得了
She will manage.
今天累死了我想去睡觉了
The day has been full.
明天还有活要干呢
There's work tomorrow.
好的 儿子 你看起来眼皮都快掉下来了
Yes, my son. Your eyes are heavy with weariness.
你老婆在等你呢 二弟 手里还拿着一本书呢
Your wife waits for you, brother, with a book in her hands.
书是可以收起来放在旁边的
Even a book can be closed and put away.
那只是一本书 你居然为了它都不瞧我一眼
It is but a book, and yet it keeps your eyes from me.
来 坐我身边
Come sit beside me.
我告诉你我看到了什么
I will tell you what I have read.
我怎么知道你真的在看书
How shall I know if you read truly?
你知道我不会撒谎的
You will know I could not make up such things.
这里 书里面说了如果每个人贪婪的下场会是什么
In this place, it tells what happens when men know only greed.
里面也说和平是怎么失去的 还有人怎么相互残杀
It tells how peace is then lost, and what men may do to each other.
太神奇了
It is magic.
你的眼睛看着这些鸟脚印 然后嘴巴就说出来了...
Your eyes pick up those bird tracks and your eyes give them to your voice...
然后我也就听到了
...and your voice gives them to my ears.
还有这里 里面还说了些杀人啊,
And here, it tells how then there is killing...
打仗啊甚至是折磨人的事情
...and fighting and even torture.
哦 折磨人是不对的
Oh, it is wrong to torture.
- 里面是这么说的啊 - 太神奇了啊
- That is what it says. - It is magic.
你都没再听我说
You do not listen.
我有在听
I try.
你用心点啊
You must try harder.
买书是要花钱的 我们可不能浪费钱
Money was spent for this book. We must not waste it.
我知道 我们也不能浪费老天给予我们的东西
We must waste nothing that is given to us.
无论是钱 还是我们在一起的时间
Neither money,nor the hours we have together.
你这样看着我 我都读不了书
I cannot read when you keep watching me.
反正我书里面的东西 我又看不懂
Since I cannot look at the book and know what it means...
我就只能看着你罗
...I must look at you...
钱不能浪费 时间也不能浪费啊
...so the money will not be wasted, and nothing else.
那我教你读书吧
Then I will teach you to read.
这个是个词
There is word here...
它的意思是说我们必须反抗所有让我们变成软蛋的事情
...of how men must rise up and resist the things that make them weak.
我可不这么认为
That is advice I cannot take.
你呢
Can you?
哎呀 你根本没在听我说话啊
Well, you will not listen.
你看 你现在又把书拿走了
And now you place the book where my hand cannot reach it.
- 那我是不是要把它放回来啊 - 是的
- Shall I put it back within your grasp? - Yes.
算了
No.
我也想睡觉了
I will rest my eyes now.
下次我再教你吧
I will teach you to read another time.
下次我要是想读书了 我再提醒你
I will remind you when I'm ready for reading.
愿老天原谅我说出这种大逆不道的话
Let the gods forgive me for saying this but I am wicked.
我爱你胜过爱我的父母
I love you more than I love my father and my mother.
我比你更加大逆不道 因为我就喜欢你说这样的话
I am more wicked than you. I want to hear you tell me this.
如果东西只够爹娘还有你吃
If there were food enough only for them or for you...
我宁可让他们挨饿 也要让你吃饱饭
...I would give it to you and let them starve.
你愿意亲近我 这可是破天荒的头一回啊
You turn to me of your own will, and it is the first time this has been so.
是的 给你今晚的奖励 因为你说了我喜欢说的话
Yes, for this night, you have told me the thing my heart needed to hear.
现在我知道你是在乎我的感受跟想法的 也开始慢慢理解我了
Now I know that you'll care what I think and feel, and what I am.
而不仅仅是想着让我给你煮饭 生儿子
Not only that I give you children and make your food.
我不仅仅属于这个家
I know that I'm not only to belong to your house...
我更属于你
...but I am to be yours.
这样我也知足了
And I am content.
你迟到了啊 是不是遇到了什么麻烦
You're late. Did you once more have trouble...
难道又逃不出我娘的法眼啦
...escaping my mother's eyes?
从今天开始 我想去哪儿就去哪儿
From this day on, I will come to you openly.
娘不会再说我什么闲话了
She will say nothing.
我可不认为娘这老顽固会变得这么快
I cannot believe my mother will change that much.
不是娘 是我
No. But I have changed.
你没看出来我有什么不同吗
Do you not see it?
你眼睛温柔了一点
Your eyes are as soft.
头发摸起来也柔软一点
Your hair as pleasant to my touch.
不过 我还是看不出来
No, I cannot see this change...
我倒是希望还是老样子
...and I do not wish a change.
是我肚子里面的
It is within me.
这变化大到连我自己 都没办法掩盖这脸上的喜悦
But it is so great I thought it must show on my face.
这又是哪门子东西引起的变化啊 又是什么时候开始的啊
What is the cause of this great difference? And when did it begin?
从我们第一次彼此敞开心扉的那个晚上开始的 老公
On the night we first opened our hearts to each other, my husband.
即使她只是个女的 我也心满意足了
Even if it is only a girl, I shall be very happy.
我们要当父母啦
We shall be ancestors?
- 他肯定是个儿子 - 我也祈求上天能赐给我一个儿子
- Oh, it will be a son. - I shall ask the gods for one.
但是如果是一个女儿 你也会爱护她吗
But if it is only a girl,she still will be welcome?
会的 只要她是我们的女儿 我就会一直爱护她
If you're her mother,she will be welcome.
然后我们教她读书
And she will be taught to read...
虽然她爹总是忙一些不起眼的粗活
...even if her father is always too busy with lesser things.
要不然这小姑娘住哪啊
Where would this upstart daughter be...
我干这些粗活不就是为了她嘛
...if I did not busy myself
with those lesser things?
天啊 我太开心了
Oh, this is a good moment.
这真是我人生遇过的最幸福的时刻了
The best in my life so far.
- 有东西掉下来了  - 看起来像银色的蛋
- Something falls. - It shines like silver.
快看地里 冒起黑色的喷泉了
Look at the earth. It's a black fountain.
一个可以容得下50个人的大坑啊
A hole big enough to bury 50 men.
还在冒烟呢
And smokes still comes from it.
如果刚刚有人站在这里 他早就见阎王去了
If one of us had stood near here, he would no longer live.
这十年来我一直想挖个池塘的 这次省事多了
I've wanted to dig a pond on my land for 10 years, and here it is.
如果那些日本鬼子 只是用他们的飞船
It would be better if the barbarians did use the sky ships...
来挖挖池塘 挖挖井的话就好了
...to dig ponds and wells.
- 听起来不错啊 - 快看 那里也冒烟了
- Maybe it is an idea. - Look. Look, rolling smoke.
跟那电影上的一样啊
It was the same in the magic pictures.
城墙都着火了 外面也是
There are many fires over the city wall and small ones outside.
- 飞船好像是从烟里面飞过来的 - 我们该怎么办
- Flying ships come out of the smoke. - What shall we do?
得有人去趟城里
Someone of us should go to the city.
我老婆担心大姐会不会出事了
My... My wife thinks of our elder sister and what happens to her.
我们都应该商量一下的 我去吧
We should all think of that. I'll go.
别着急 老表 如果是好事 它不会长了腿自己跑掉的
I would not be hasty, cousin. If it is good news, it will not spoil.
但是如果是坏事 早去晚去都一样
The more slowly one hears bad news, the better.
我走还是不走 我那老婆子可不会让我干等着
My woman wouldn't let me rest if I didn't go, nor could I rest.
- 让我跟你一起去吧 爹 - 好 快点
- Let me go in your place. - All right, go quickly.
看看你能帮上什么忙 大伙赶紧都回去干活吧
Do what you can. The rest of us should go back to our work.
不会是我们儿子吧 真不敢相信啊
Can it be our son at last? I'm afraid to believe it is.
我们死定了 我们死定了
We're all but dead. We're all but dead.
离街十步远都可能被杀掉啊
We might have been killed had we been 10 feet nearer to street.
天要塌下来了啊 天要塌下来了啊
There was such noise.There was such noise.
商店都关了一半了
The shop half gone.
除了烂命一条 我们现在什么都没有了
We have nothing but our bare lives in our hands.
什么都没有了 什么都没有了
We're lost. All is lost. All.
从早到晚 飞船飞来飞去
All day the flying ships came.
然后炸弹掉下来 房子就炸成了灰烬
And everywhere the silver eggs dropped, they burst the buildings into dust.
店铺跟货物全毁了
And the shops and all the goods within are waste.
- 人怎么样了啊 - 人
- But what of the people? - The people...
都炸成块了 就像瓦片一样炸成碎片了
Into pieces, as if they were made of clay.
- 东一条胳膊 西一个头的 一块一块的... - 为什么啊 为什么啊
- Here an arm, there a head, there a piece... - But why? Why?
怎么可以这样对待其他人呢 我们可是在同一片天空下生活的呀
How can men do this to other men? The sky is over us all.
我们的佣人都死了
Our own servants and the clerks are dead.
多老实忠厚的一个年轻小伙啊 我们下次去哪里找这样一个人啊
And one such an honest young man.Where shall we find one like him again?
现在老实人也没人要了 哪里还有店铺需要伙计帮忙的啊
What is the use, even of an honest man,if there's no shop to put him in?
我们的店 我们的货啊 全完蛋了啊 全完了
Our shops, our goods, gone, all gone.
我只是一个想过太平日子的生意人而已啊
I'm a man who can prosper only in peace.
难道那些学生说的事情都是真的啊
Can it be those students who cried out spoke the truth?
真的 现在什么才是真的
The truth? Now, what is the truth?
还有谁能分得清真假
Each men sees it differently.
我听到的是 东洋鬼子要过来了
The truth I see is that the East Ocean people will come...
他们会打进城里 然后占领整个城市的
...and enter the city, and the city will fall.
- 然后 国家也就快了 - 怎么可能
- Yes, and so will the nation. - Can that be?
我们国家都是人 我们不就是那些人吗
The nation is only the people, and we are the people.
- 我们人活着 国家就应该还在啊 - 我们还不够强大啊
- And while we remain, so does the nation. - We're not strong enough.
为什么不够强大 我们难道没有可以杀人的东西吗
Why are we not strong enough? Why do we not have things to kill with too?
我们这些农村人对他们而言没什么用
They have no use to people like us who love only to live.
这样我们可就死定了啊
Then we will die.
人固有一死的 不过我觉得不应该是这个样子的
Death is each men's natural end, and that I know. But not this kind.
人人都这么想过 除非他亲身经历过
This is beyond the mind of man unless he sees it for himself.
我得做些什么事情
That I must do.
快一点 那是我老公啊
Hurry. It is my husband.
他被埋在废墟里面了
He's here beneath this rubbish.
这是他的手啊 我认得出来
It is his hand! I would know it anywhere.
我的天啊!
Oh, my God!
这场面有点让人受不了 我不会怪你的孩子
It is too much to bear, and I do not blame you.
看看我们能帮忙做些什么事情 过来
We must see what can be done here. Come.
村里都快被逃难的人流围成了孤岛了
Our village has become an island in a river of fleeing people.
但是他们都被吓到走不动了
But they cannot run fast enough to forget the horror behind them.
爷爷有事要跟大伙说
My grandfather will speak to you now.
我知道你们希望我可以帮你们解决眼前这些麻烦事
I know that you are looking to me to save you from this great trouble.
但是我没办法 我已经试过了
I've been trying to find a way but I cannot.
我现在连自己都救不了
I cannot save myself.
我估计明天也还会是今天这样子
I know that what today was will be again tomorrow.
你们啊 我三个儿子啊 都是男子汉了 还有你吴连 你最年长
You, my three sons, are men. And you, Wu Lien, are older than they.
- 你们大伙也来说说看 - 我...
- If you have anything to say, then say it. - I...
我也还没有想不出什么好方法可以救我们
I have not yet thought of any way to save any of us.
眼下只有两条路可以走
There are two things which can be done.
要不然就是逃难去 躲开这些洋鬼子
One is to escape the evil by running away.
要不然就是留在这里听天由命
And the other is to let it come down and bear it.
如果这样的话 爹 你会选哪一个
In this, my father, I ask, what will you do yourself?
我会留下 这里可是生我养我的地方
Stay here where I was born and where I have lived.
那我也跟你一起留下来
Then I say I will do what you do.
我也留下
I, too, will stay.
但是 爹 我想逃难去
But I, my father, will escape it.
你们要走我没意见
I will say nothing to any who do go.
留下来的人就跟我留下 想走的就走
Let those who will stay with me, and those who would go, let them go.
你这是在责备我吗 爹
You blame me, my father?
不是不是 我不责怪你 我的儿啊
No, no. I do not blame you, my son.
那我就按计划逃难去
Then do as I will do. Leave this place.
我也想把地像布料一样卷起来带走 这样好跟你一起逃难去...
If I could roll up my land like a cloth and take it with me...
但是这是不可能的事情啊
...but that is impossible. No.
我留下 儿子 你走就是
No. I stay, my son. You are free to go.
我不想怕是因为我有所顾虑
I do not run away because I'm afraid.
我担心我没出生的孩子
I only fear for my coming child.
我有孙子啦
A grandchild?
这是好消息啊 儿子
That is good news, my son.
这样你更应该走了
And I think it well that you go.
你打算什么时候走 老二
When will you leave us, brother?
我们还没有决定
We have yet time.
我们会等到有合适的人 再一起走
We will wait until we find those we would go with.
我可不认为这样做是好的 我觉得小玉应该留下来把小孩生下
I do not like this talk. I do not see why Jade should be taken away.
是不是只要这样我才能照顾我的小孩呢 娘
It is only that I may finish what I was made to do, my mother.
我是怕你生产的时候 谁还来照顾你啊
But who will look after you when your time comes?
我孙子不可能像个畜生一样在荒郊野外出生啊
Why should our grandson be born somewhere in a field like an animal?
他们最好还是离开这里
It may be better that they go.
因为我们不知道会发生什么 说不定陌生人就闯进门了呢
We do not know what lies ahead. Strange feet may enter our gate.
如果我儿子要走 我不拦他 但是小玉得留下
If my son wants to go, he will go. But let Jade stay.
怎么说她怀的可是老凌家的骨肉啊
我觉得不应该留下
Her duty to you comes first.
I think it does not.
女人应该陪着她丈夫一起走的
A woman should go with her man.
最近很多人从这里逃难过去了
There are so many who flee these past weeks.
地里面的路都被走变形了
The whole face of the earth must be changing.
老表 那又是什么东西
Cousin, what comes now?
他们好像拖着奇怪的玩意儿
These carry different burdens.
前进!
Move along!
注意看路
Keep to the road!
这又是什么蠢东西啊
What foolishness is this?
只有城里人才会费力气去背一堆破铜烂铁
Only a city man would break his back under the weight of iron...
而不去背大米
...when he might carry a bag of rice.
你们这些人怎么不弄两个轮子造个车子 拖这些东西啊
Why did you not take two wheels and make a cart and ride?
看看这些蠢蛋 都快把这些金属玩意吃到肚子里了去了
Look at those fools. They will eat iron if they eat at all.
这不是金属 聪明的乡下朋友啊 我们搬的可是工厂的机器啊
This is not iron, my wise country friend.This is a factory we carry on our backs.
你们会慢慢习惯的
And you may as well get used to seeing such things...
后面还有整个城市跟着我们呢
...for a whole city follows behind us.
他们跟其他人不一样 好像有组织有计划的
These are not as the others were. They seem to have a plan.
停!
Halt!
我们就地休息一会
停!
We will rest now for a little while.
Halt!
休息!
Rest!
我从来没有像今天这么累过
I've never been so tired.
你们怎么不在地里头休息啊
Why do you not sleep here in our land?
这里还有水 我们可以分给你们一些
There is water, and we will share what we can with you.
你人真好老大爷 但是我们不能离得太远
You are good to us as all have been, or we could not have come this far.
我们今晚得守着这些机器睡觉 我的农民朋友
We will rest here tonight with these, our friends.
我们打算跟这些人一起走 爹
These are the people we will join, my father.
是的 他们就是我们要等的人
Yes. They are the ones we have waited for.
他们有坚定的决心跟必胜的勇气
They are strong and full of courage.
兄弟啊 我想问问你 你们这是要去哪里啊
I would ask you, my friend, where do you go?
我们的目的地在山上 离这里一千多里远
Our eyes are on the mountains, a thousand miles from here.
那你们去哪里做什么呀
What will you do there, sir?
我们打算去安装这些机器 然后建立一个兵工厂
We'll set up these machines we carry, and they will be a factory.
为前线的抗日部队造枪支弹药
Then we'll make bullets and guns for the army.
那我们的部队呢
Where is our brave army now?
他们在前线跟鬼子打仗呢
They fight between you and the Japanese.
许多战士为了拖延鬼子为我们争取时间 都已经壮烈牺牲了
Many thousands of them have already died to delay the evil dwarfs from coming here.
我儿子可不可以加入你们的队伍
My son would join you in your journey if he is welcome.
我们欢迎你家的任何人加入我们
We would be happy to take something of yours with us.
再带上他老婆你看行不
And what is a man without his wife?
我够强壮 可以帮上忙的
I, too, am strong and can be of help.
好吧 我们也欢迎你
You are welcome also.
这大风 看样子是要下雨了 对我们种田的是好事
The wind has brought rain. It is good for our land...
-但是对你们行军的就不好了吧 -如果对你们是好的 对我们也好
- ...but is it not bad for travelers? - If it helps you, then it must help us.
我们马上要出发了 我还在担心是不是有点远呢
Now that we are to go, I wonder if it's too far.
就算别人倒下了 我也会继续前进的
I will be on my feet when others drop.
- 我真希望我能帮你带着小孩  -早晚有一天你会的
- I wish I could carry the child for you. - One of these days you shall.
我从来没想过我的孩子会出生在这样的地方..
I never thought a child of mine would be born anywhere...
居然不是在这片土地上
...except here on this land.
他会找到属于自己的天地的
He will find a place of his own.
但是对任何一个人而言 他的出生地总是值得纪念的
It is very meaningful to a man where he is born.
我们得留个纪念在这里啊
We must mark the place.
他还没出生 人生就已经从这里开始了
A man begins his life before he is born.
没有比我们这棵大树更适合做记号的地方了
So, what better place to mark for him than our tree.
刻在那里...这样它也成了我们跟孩子的了
There. Now it will be his also.
好了 大伙准备了!
All right, take your places!
- 各就各位!- 各就各位!
- Take you places. - Take your places!
我们必须在中午休息之前翻过这座大山
We must cross those hills before the midday rest.
各就各位!
Take your places!
我到处找了 还是没找到娘...
I've looked everywhere but I cannot find our mother...
好跟她道别的
...to say goodbye.
爹 告诉娘 我们很难过没有来得及跟她老人家道别
Tell her it is our sorrow that we could not find her.
我会转告她的 你们赶紧 别让别人等你们
I will tell her. You must not keep your friends waiting.
记得 如果小孩出生的话 给我们报个信
Send me word somehow when the child is born.
如果是个男孩 装一根红线在里面
If it is a boy, send a red cord in the envelope.
如果是女孩 就装根蓝色的
If it is a girl, let it be a blue one.
记住了孩子
Remember, my child...
女人是根 男人是树
...that the woman is a root, and the man the tree.
根固才能树茂啊.
The tree grows only as high as the root is strong.
我记住了爹
I will remember, my father.
走吧
Go.
这是你的任务
This place is yours.
- 前进! - 前进!
- March! - March!
原来你在这里啊
So this is where you have been.
他们到处找你
They looked for you.
我不想跟他告别
I would not come to see him go.
看着他像牛一样被喝着拉着一堆破机器
Pulling, straining like an ox and bawling like one.
- 你怎么哭了  - 哪里有
- You have been weeping. - I have not.
被水花溅到而已
Splashed water on my face.
他站在其他人旁边 看起来那么的瘦弱
He looked so small beside the others.
哪里瘦弱 老二可是我们家最强壮的
He did not. He was the largest by far.
你是天底下最了不起的母亲啦 大洋彼岸都找不到更好的啦
You are the best mother in the province. Where is there one better beyond the seas?
我傻透了
I'm a fool.
我都开始想他们了 即便是小玉
I miss them already. Even Jade.
是啊是啊 虽然他们走了 但是家里还是有一股劲儿在的
Yes, yes, some sort of strength has left the house with their going.
我可没说我要他们回来
I would not say I want them back.
他们想走就走 我可不拦他们
They want to go, they go.
我才不相信你冷酷无情呢 我还是更喜欢心直口快的你
I would not have you a cool, thin soul. I like you hot-tempered and gusty.
你个老不死的
You old turnip.
来吧 老头子 让我看看你脖子上的红点是怎么回事
Come here, old man. Let me see that spot on your neck.
- 会不会长了疖子什么的啊  - 肯定是蚊子咬的
- See if you have boil after all these years... - It's where a mosquito bit me.
不要告诉我怎么回事的 我自己来瞧瞧
Do not tell me what it is.I can see for myself.
瞧 你是不是现在老到不能打蚊子了
Well, can you not catch a mosquito anymore?
是不是跟个小屁孩一样被咬到呱呱叫
Must you be bitten like a child?
瞧你个熊样
You're clumsy.
你看 我就喜欢你口无遮拦 哪怕总是惹毛我
I like your quick tongue even when it is turned on me.
老婆子啊 我告诉你
Old woman, I tell you this.
如果你先死了 我不会再娶的
If you should die before I die, even then I would not marry another.
没了你 这日子啊就像腌萝卜不放盐 一点味道都没有了
For after you, any would be like a carrot dried without salt.
敌人的枪声越来越近了
The guns of the enemy came ever closer.
人们也开始逃难
And still the people fled before them.
凌谭的乡亲们也都四处逃难了
Some of the kinsmen of Ling Tan fled also.
不过大多数人都还是留下了 继续在地里收割庄稼
But most of them stayed and went into the fields to reap the grain.
人们相互帮忙
And each man helped his neighbor...
只有有了收成 他们才像个农民
... for the harvest was at hand,and they were farmers.
无论战乱还是和平 他们都知道 总得有人种田好吃饱肚子
And war or no war, they knew they must bring their food from the earth...
所以无论什么事情来临 他们都得喂饱家里的每一个人
... so that whatever came, they could feed their families.
日复一日 飞机来了又走
Day after day, the flying ships came...
继续轰炸着城里
... and then flew on and bombed the city.
凌家沟的人 也整天提心吊胆
The people of the valley of Ling were afraid.
但是也只是偶尔看看天 然后就低头继续干活了
But they stopped only to look up and then turn back to their work...
他们也听说了 日本鬼子占领了...
... for they'd heard that the Japanese had taken the land...
沿岸以内几百里的土地了
... a hundred miles deep from the sea...
而且现在 正在向他们的城市逼近
... and were even now approaching the nearby city.
时间变得越来越紧迫了
Time, too, had become their enemy.
老天好像刻意跟他们作对一样
It seemed nature itself was against them.
今年雨季来的比往年要早
The rains were early that year.
农民们既得跟风斗 又得跟雨斗 年复一年都如此
And the farmers fought the wind and the water as they always had.
但是这些事情是他们可以弄明白的 这些事情也是可以克服的
Here was a thing they understood and, understanding, could defeat.
但是内心的恐惧 却是无法克服的
But they could not defeat the fear that was in them.
耳朵里天天都是炸弹轰炸的声音
For always in their ears was the sound of the bombardment.
震耳欲聋
A sound that was louder now...
他们也大概猜到 鬼子的部队离这里已经不远了
... and they knew that the enemy was storming the gates of the city.
然而这一天还是降临了
Then the day came.
这是凌谭最害怕的一天
The day that Ling Tan dreaded above all others.
枪声突然消失了
The guns were silent...
飞机也不见了
... and the flying ships were gone from the air.
相比打仗的声音 我更怕这种寂静
I fear this quiet more than the noise of battle.
因为它并不代表着和平
It does not mean peace.
我们现在必须面对另外一种可能
It means but one thing, and we must face it.
那就是城里已经失守了
The defenders of our city have been overcome.
此时此刻 说不定敌人就在门外面等着
And even now as I speak to you, the enemy is at our gates.
- 不出几个小时 他们就打过来 - 这是真的
- Within hours, they will be upon us. - That is true.
敌人走那么快 我们有没有武器
The enemy moves swiftly, and we have no arms.
我们怎么反抗啊 难道用手啊
How can we resist him? Are we to fight him with our hands?
我来说说 你们听听看看
I speak for myself but you are welcome to listen.
我们阻止不了日本人
We cannot stop the Japanese, no.
但是只要他们占领了城里
But as soon as they have occupied a city...
我相信我们还是有办法的
...I believe we shall be able to deal with them.
你为什么怎么说
How can you say this?
我跟我父亲都日本人做过生意
I bought and sold their goods as did my father before me...
他们很友善的 从来不翻脸
...and I have found no great evil in the face they turned to me.
只有那些毛头大学生跟我翻脸过
I did find evil in my own people, in green boys...
他们莫名其妙把我的店跟货物砸得稀巴烂
...who burned my goods without reason.
吴连 如果他们来了你安然无事 我就相信你真的安然无事
Wu Lien, if when they come, you are right, I will say you are.
万一他们翻脸了 我们除了听他们的话之外 还能做些什么呢
But even if you are not, what can we do but take their rule for ours also?
我们只求太平日子 安享晚年而已
All we want is peace and to be left alone to live.
- 时间紧迫啊 我们有什么计划啊 - 我们应该怎么迎接他们
- Our time is short. What is the plan? - How shall we meet them?
我们应该怎么表明我们的态度
How can we show them what is in our hearts?
我们除了自己之外还能知道什么呢 还是顺其自然吧
What ways do we know but our own? Let us do what we would do...
无论谁来了 我们至少有点骨气吧
...for any new ruler coming to our village, but let us keep our pride.
这都是些机器啊
But they are machines.
我们怎么跟这些冒烟的机器谈判的
How can you talk to machines when they're belching smoke?
- 敌人来了 快去跟他们说 - 别敌人敌人的
- Speak, here is the enemy. - Do not use that word.
太君
Sirs...
太君 我仅代表...
Sirs, I am come...
太君 我们仅代表本村 ..
We are come, sirs...
太君 我们都是农民
Sir, we are only farmers...
还有一两个生意人跟读书人
...a small merchant or two, and my cousin here the scholar.
- 我们都是明事理的老实人... - 你们的旅馆在哪里
- We are men of peace and reason... - Where is your inn, farmer?
- 带我们过去  - 但是...
- Lead us there. - But...
店小二 店小二 来给我的士兵们倒水
Waiter. Waiter. Service for my soldiers.
你们过去 靠墙边站好
You there, line up against the wall.
- 站好 老实点 别惹麻烦 - 我们还是走吧
- Steady, now. Give us no trouble. - Let's get out of here.
把他带过来 马上
Get him over here, right now.
- 你病了吗 爹  - 不 不 不 没事
- You are ill, my father. - No, no, no. It's nothing.
- 上酒  - 上酒
- Wine with it. - Wine, wine.
拿过来
Over here.
给我拿酒来 不然我一枪毙了你
Wine.Bring the wine or we'll shoot you.
这是茶 我们要的是酒 不要茶!
Tea. We want wine, not tea.
- 酒   - 是的 我们要酒
- Wine? - Yes, wine.
但是我们这里没有酒啊
We... We have no wine.
我们只有过节的时候才有酒啊
We have that only on feast days.
哦 没有酒啊
Oh, no wine, huh?
那总有女人吧
And where are your women?
拿出点东西来犒劳一下皇军啊
There are other things than wine.
对 女人
Women.
带女人过来 给我年轻点的
Bring them. Bring me a young one.
老少都无所谓 我只要她们可以....
I do not care if mine is young or not. What matters so long as they are...
还有人敢逃跑吗
Does anyone else care to run?
我们家里有酒 好酒
We have wine in our homes. Good wine.
我们会让女人拿过来给你们的
We will have our women bring it to you.
那就看着他们拿过来
See that they do, then.
别停下 快走
No, do not stop.
你们赶紧回家
Get to your homes.
老太婆 老太婆
Old woman. Old woman.
快让全家人过来 鬼子来了
Get the household together inside quickly. The enemy comes.
小兰 大女儿 大伙快来
Orchid, eldest daughter, all of you.
- 怎么啦 - 带上孩子们
- What? - Bring the children.
- 老三啊 儿子啊 - 谈判如何啦
- Lao San, my son. - What of the speech?
我们用嘴巴跟枪口谈判啊!
Our mouths spoke into the mouths of guns.
快跟我来
Come with me.
你们必须分头走 每个人照顾好自己的家人
You must scatter over the lands. Each man look after his own.
老三照顾老太太 我守在家里
My third son, his mother. I'll stay with the house.
- 我跟你一起 - 不行
- I'll stay by you. - No, you cannot.
- 我要爬到屋梁上面躲起来 - 那我也一起爬上去
- I'll climb the rafters and hide there. - Then I'll climb also.
他们沿着路边过来了
They come by the road.
- 娘  - 等等 等一下
- Mother. - Oh, no, no, wait.
不 不 那边会被他们发现的
No, this way.They will see us there.
我们必须躲起来 找一下墙上有个洞
We must hide. Find the hole in the wall.
这边 儿子
Here. My son.
小兰 带着孩子
Orchid. Take the baby.
孩子们 你们要勇敢一点 我们很快就安全了
Come, my son, you must be brave. We will be soon be safe.
安全 哪里还安全啊
Safety. Where is safety?
娘 快 快 娘
Mother, please. Please, Mother.
她走不动了
She can go no further.
- 你们走 我来照顾她   - 好 好 我....
- Go. I will do my best for your mother. - Yes. Yes, I...
- 我娘... - 记住了...
- My mother. - Remember...
照顾好自己人 其他人就不用管了
...let each look out for those in his charge and pay no heed to the others.
我们得各自找个安全的地方躲起来 每个人都找找
We must hide safely, and each group to itself.
是的 是的 要是一个被发现了 其他人也就完了
Yes, yes. Then if one is found, only they perish.
走 我们把你藏起来 轻点 轻点
Go. We must hide you. Quiet, quiet.
别乱动 别出声 我们就在附近
Do not move. Do not speak. We will not be far away.
- 老头 你个缩头乌龟 - 门锁上了
- Old man, hermit. - The door is locked.
我们的老狗 会被他们杀死的
Our old dog. They will kill him.
有用的就拿走 没用的就通通砸掉
Take what you want and destroy the rest.
还有什么值钱的东西没
Is there anything here worth having?
人都跑光了 屋里一个人都没有
All of them are gone. No one is in the house.
你呆在这里 大儿子 像个男子汉一样
You will stay here, my eldest son, like a man and by yourself.
趴下 缩紧身子到地里面
Lie down, make yourself small against the ground.
你呆在这里千万别乱动 老婆 无论发生什么事情
And you here, my wife. Do not move for anything.
你这是要去哪
Where will you go?
回去一会 我得去看看前面鬼子那里
Back a little, between you and the evil thing there.
好的 老公
Yes, my husband.
你在发抖
You tremble.
别吓得跟个兔子似的
Your nose twitches like a little rabbit.
走吧 别在这里浪费时间 我们去找那个老农民
Come, do not waste time here. Find the farmer.
搜搜院子里头
Search the courtyard.
这里搜到的第一个女人就归我啦
And the first woman we find belongs with me.
院子里有没有出去的路
Is there a way out of this courtyard?
这里 这边墙上有个洞
Here. Here's a hole in the wall.
把蔓藤拉开 有人刚从这里爬过去了
Pull aside the vine. Someone has crawled through here.
伙计们快来看看 我找到了什么
Come, see what I found.
他们留下来点东西
Something they left behind.
难怪啊 大伙快来瞧瞧
No wonder. Look at it.
刚刚谁说的第一个女人归他的啊
Here is the first woman and she belongs to you.
不 她老了 不会有事的
No. She is old.
他们只会动年轻女人的主意
There are the young to think of.
别怕
Do not be afraid.
老公
My husband.
来 儿子 我们换个安全一点的地方
Come, my son, we'll be safer in another place.
我听到小孩子的声音
I heard a child.
有小孩 那就是有女人咯
Where there is a child, there is a woman.Dragon Seed
记住 男子汉大丈夫 看到什么都不要哭
Remember, a little man does not cry out. No matter what he sees.
死亡的气息离远了
The sounds of death are far away now.
我的上好红箱子啊
My good red pigskin boxes...
那可是我的嫁妆啊
...that I brought here as a bride.
来吧老太婆
Come, old woman.
院子里才糟糕呢
There's worse to see in the courtyard.
你站在这里
Wait here.
别挡住我
Do not spare me what you must see.
有人来了
Someone comes.
有人在吗
Is anybody here?
是老三
It's our third son.
爹 娘
Mother. Father.
- 你们没事啊 - 是的是的 我们没事 老三
- You are safe. - Yes, yes, we are safe.
- 我们都没事  - 你哥嫂他们呢
- We're safe.  - Where's your brother and his family?
我也不知道 我们走散了之后就没再见过了
I don't know. We lost each other
and did not come together again.
- 坐下来先  - 其他人呢
- Sit down. - Where are the others?
听人说 洋学堂的人都没事
We met people who told us it was safe in the foreign school in the city.
- 大姐跟孩子们都在里面 - 吴连呢
- My sister and her children are there. - Where then is Wu Lien?
可能跟大姐在一起吧
Perhaps he stayed in safety with our daughter.
他说要回去店里面一趟
He went back to his shop and he will stay there, he said.
但是他怎么回去我就不清楚了
But how he can, I do not know.
到处都是女人跟小孩的尸体 到处都是血
The women, little children. Streets run with their blood.
村子里面 女人都被弄死在草丛里...
In the village, the young women are dead in the grass.
没人知道有多少人还活着...
And no one knows how many others still live...
生不如死啊
...but would be better dead.
老天啊 这都发生了什么啊
Oh, what I have seen this night.
天啊 天啊!
Oh, I cannot. I cannot.
来来来 我的小乖孙子啊
There, there, my meat dumpling.
小兰 她以前是多么的傻 多么的胆小怕事啊
She was ever a poor, foolish little thing, without courage.
但是她不愧是我老婆
But she was my wife.
我要离开这里
I cannot stay here. I cannot.
安静点 儿子 这可是你的家
Quiet, my son. This is your home.
不再是了 我恨死这个鬼地方了
No longer. I hate it.
去哪里都无所谓 我就是不想继续呆在这里
I do not care where I go, but I cannot stay here.
我要跑到山里面加入游击队 然后打死这帮鬼子
I will go with those in the hills who fight this horror.
你也得休息一下先啊 现在别想太多
Rest today first. Do not think of it now.
我不想休息 我必须马上走
I cannot rest. I must go.
帮帮老三收拾一下行李吧
Help our third son make ready for his journey.
记住啊儿子 痛苦终会过去的
Remember, my son,all weeping ceases at last.
你弟弟比较鲁莽 我希望你能多留心他一下
Your brother's rash and foolish,and I will keep an eye on him.
我自己不能盯着他 也只能拜托给其他人了
If not my own, then one that I can trust.
我要你也一起进山 帮我照顾好他
I would have you follow him to the hills and watch over him for me.
- 你这是命令我吗 爹  - 是的
- Do you so command me, Father? - I do.
山里
The hills.
在山里我也可以杀鬼子
There I, too, could fight.
对 好让鬼子们血债血偿
Yes, I can pay these dwarfs some of what I owe them.
我巴不得一巴掌就拍死他们一堆
I could kill them like lice in a winter coat.
从昨天开始 我们都是白发人送黑发人了 老表
Since this time yesterday, cousin,we have both lost sons.
- 这公鸡还知道报晓 - 已经没什么必要了
- Can a cock still crow? - It does not seem one should.
我都感觉看不到明天了
I feel there is no tomorrow.
请进请进 太君
Come in. Come in, sirs.
- 腌鱼有没有  - 鱼 有有有 太君
- Salted fish. - Fish, yes. Yes, sir.
你的鱼 太君 哎呀 哎呀!
Here, here is fish. Oh, no.
怎么啦
What...?
我真是天打五雷劈啊
I'm of all creatures, the most unfortunate.
我这鱼还没有腌制好啊 太君 只是稍微泡了一下油而已
These fish are not salted. No, no, sir.They are only soaked in oil.
- 没事 我拿走 - 那就送给你了 太君
- I will take them. - Then take them as a gift, please.
反正都是我从贵国进口的 这样也算是物归原主了
I bought them from your country and now I return them to you.
- 谢谢你 你是吴连吧 - 是的 太君
- Thank you. You are Wu Lien? - Yes, sir.
- 你不恨我们  - 为什么要恨呢 我不恨任何人的 太君
- And you do not hate us? - Why, no. I hate no one, sir.
谢谢你 对于你店里的损失我深感遗憾
Thank you.For all this damage we are sorry.
- 我们的士兵都比较鲁莽 - 没事 我理解 我理解 我理解皇军的
- Our soldiers very brave, angry. - Oh, yes, I know. I know how soldiers are.
-我都祈祷有太平日子过的-天下太平了 我们生意人才能赚钱嘛
- But now... Now let us hope for peace. - Only in peace can we do business.
很高兴认识你这样的人
I am glad to meet a man who hates no one.
如果有什么其他事情 你尽管吩咐 太君
What can I say except that whatever you want me to do I will do.
你可能对我们会有点用处 如果你懂得做人的话
You maybe useful to us, if you will.
你觉得我不懂做人么
Will I not be...?
我们打算建立一个临时政府
We shall set up a people's government here.
然后找一些听话的人帮我们办事 你识字的吧
And those who rule, shall rule for us. Can you read and write?
我识字的 太君 我可是个文化人啊
Oh, certainly, sir. I'm a man of culture.
- 那你应该认识这个地址吧 - 认识 认识 太君
- You know the address written there? - Yes. Yes, sir.
我以前送货去过那里 那可是一个有钱人的大房子啊
I have delivered goods there.It is the house of a very rich man.
现在这个房子是我们的了 房子的主人也在为我们办事了
And now he shares it with us,his friends.
你明天也搬过来跟我们一起吧
You will come there tomorrow.And live there.
你会看到皇军对于服从的人是多么的慷慨
You'll see how merciful we are with those who do not resist us.
好的 太君
Yes.
这门上的大日本帝国国旗会保护你 一直到你搬过来为止
Our flag above your door will protect you until you come to us.
谢天 谢地 谢太君啊
All my thanks, great one. Oh, even to 10,000 thousand.
真庆幸我忍了这么几个月 如今我又可以跟家人团聚了
I'm more cheered than I've been for months.Now I can be with my household again.
我如此精打细算 简直就是诸葛亮在世啊
How wise am I to arrange my own affairs so well.
- 又死了一个  爱国者啊 什么是爱国
- Another patriot has died. - Patriot. What, then, is a patriot?
难道就得为了国家而丢了自己的小命
To be one must a man die and let the worms eat his flesh?
不 不 不 我可不这么想
No, no, no. I think not.
这些国家的事情都不关我的事
All these thing that happen are not my affair.
无论外面什么世道 我只是本分的生意人而已
Whatever comes, I'm a man of peace.
老天给我什么东西 我就卖什么东西
And whatever heaven sends I will take and go on with my business.
如果大伙都停止这些愚蠢的抵抗 估计天下早就太平了
If this foolish resistance will stop there will be peace.
你不觉得吗
Do you not agree?
农民们 以后这村子归皇军管了
Farmer, this country now belongs to us, your conquerors.
只有经过皇军同意 你们才可以种地
You must produce on your land as we say.
所有的收成也归我们所有 价钱也由我们决定
And the harvest is to come to us at the price we tell you it shall be.
不听皇军命令的人 将不会再有耕地
And those who disobey us will need their land no longer.
- 但是他们抓走了我的鱼啊 那可是我的池塘 - 你什么也没有了
- But they take all the fish. The pond is mine. - Nothing is yours.
你们难道都不明白 你们村已经被占领了吗
Will you village men never learn that you are conquered?
太君啊 你们拿走了所有粮食 来年我们怎么生活 怎么播种啊
If they take all the rice, how can we live and plant in the spring?
你身上的脂肪也够你生活的了
You can live off your own fat and you will be given seed when the time come.
你们把所有畜生都牵走了啊
You don't even leave us breeding stock.
我们帮你们养着 皇军是需要吃肉的
We will raise the animals henceforth and also eat them.
没了牛 谁来犁地啊
My ox. Who will pull the plow?
你看起来也蛮强壮的啊
Your own back looks strong.
我们孙子该怎么办啊
How would we feed our grandchildren now?
- 你怎么就不敢反抗了呢 - 我活着 才能保住我的土地啊
- Why did you not defy him? - Alive, I can hold my land.
如果死了 我就只能被埋在地里头了
Dead, I can only hold so much as I am buried in.
当凌谭跟他的乡亲们努力维持生计的时候
So while Ling Tan and his kinsmen tried somehow to live on...
那些兵工厂的人 正在用他们的双手
... those who had taken machines apart with their hands...
一块一块的搬运机器继续前进
... so they could be carried piece by piece,were making their way forward.
泥泞阻挡不了他们 大雨也不行
Mud could not stop them. Nor could rain.
滂沱大雨淹没了一切
Rain that so filled the air that fish could have lived in it.
泥巴像阎王爷的小鬼一样 缠住了他们双脚
Mud so thick that it held them back like evil hands.
河流三番两次切断了前进的道路
Water was made to cross and it was crossed many times.
人们无法前进时 他们开始造船
And when it could not be walked in,boats were built.
他们渡过江 渡过河
And the people rowed upon the water.
在江河上 谈笑风生
And were grateful for the moment that they need not walk.
时间随着他们的脚步 一点一点流逝
Time came when the earth opened at their feet...
但是他们永不止步
... but they did not stop.
他们用破布、腰带 绳子做起了桥
They took what they had, rags and belts and ropes, and made bridges...
然后继续前进
... and passed over.
最后他们终于到了到了高山道
And then they reached the high mountain passes...
一个没人到过的地方
... where no one had gone before.
许多人饿到走不动了 一点力气都没有了
And many faltered, for food was gone and strength was near an end.
人们步履蹒跚但是仍继续坚持
Many faltered but did not stop.
没有什么可以阻挡他们前进的意志
Nothing could stop them but their own will.
老二跟小玉也是一样
Nor could it stop Jade and Lao Er.
虽然时不时他们要休息一下
Although now and then, they rested...
小玉也在盼望能早点到达目的地
... and she yearned for the end of the journey...
因为她自己清楚小孩子快出生了
... for she knew that her time was at hand.
此时此刻 日本鬼子漫山遍野 肆虐着这片土地
The enemy was everywhere,leaving footprints on the sick earth...
凌谭的乡亲们死了很多人
... and many of Ling Tan's kinsmen died.
有些人很快被杀死了 更惨的是另外一些人
Some met death quickly but they were the fortunate ones.
只能等着被活活饿死冻死
For others found a longer, harder way to die.
闹完饥荒 瘟疫也开始肆虐
And then starvation came,and pestilence...
老凌一家也在劫难逃
... and did not spare the house of Ling Tan.
谭家的孙子们也病倒了 因为他们一直体弱多病
The little children were struck down for they were the weakest.
老凌头夫妻两个无奈地跑到地里头
So Ling Tan and his wife went into the fields...
挖草根 捡谷粒
... to dig for roots and forgotten kernels of grain.
凌家沟到处都是饥肠辘辘的人
All about them were the other people of the valley.
人们饿到发疯了似的
And the hunger pain in their bellies drove some of them mad...
他们像禽兽一样为了一点吃的大打出手
... and they became as animals and fought each other.
还有些人跟乞丐似的
Some of them fell upon their knees...
为了一些猪都不吃的泔水 而打得死去活来
... and fought for swill that not even swine would eat...
而鬼子们却站在旁边冷笑
... while the enemy laughed.
但是老凌头跟其他农民一样 依旧坚守着自己的土地
But still, Ling Tan and others like him clung to their land.
老太婆
Old woman?
我找了点吃的
I have found food for them.
孙女死了
Girl is dead.
孙子呢 我们还有吃的 给他吃点东西
But the boy... There is food.We can help him.
太迟了 回天无力了
It's too late. He is past all help.
这家里没了孙子 还能叫做家吗
What is a house where no children are?
他们带来欢乐 如今他们一走 这家也就乐不起来了
They brought only happiness and they have taken it away.
老天啊 你为什么要带走他们啊
What need could the gods have of them?
为什么不是我这个老骨头而偏偏是我的孙子们啊
That should I go on living when my grandchildren die.
我诅咒这些战争犯
Curse all these men who would make wars.
我诅咒他们全家
Curse all women who give birth to these men.
我诅咒他们祖宗十八代
And curse their grandmothers and all who are their kin.
为什么通情达理的人都不联合起来
Why do not men of peace and sense band together...
反抗这些制造战争的畜生呢
...and forbid life to those who would make wars?
我现在该怎么办啊
Yet what can I do?
我一个人又能如何啊
One man upon my land.
老表 老表在家吗
Cousin, cousin? Are you here, then?
老表在家吗 老表 人都跑哪里去了
Cousin, are you here, then? Cousin, cousin? Where is the man?
我有个天大的消息告诉你啊
I come with big news in my mouth.
你看看 他家还有吃的呢
See. See, they have food and did not share it.
有你儿子的信 我从茶屋带过来的
This is from your son. A messenger brought it to the teahouse.
我可从来没收到过我儿子写的信
A letter from a son is something I will never have now.
我们都一无所有了
We have all lost much.
快快快 打开瞧瞧
Well, then, open it.
一根红线
The cord is red.
- 是个孙子! - 我们又有多了个孙子!
- It is a son. - We have a grandson.
你哭啥啊 应该高兴才对啊
But you weep. This is a time for joy.
高兴啥 刚刚死了两个
Two grandchildren lie dead in our house.
我是不是该谢谢老天爷 送回来一个给我了啊
Shall I thank heaven for sending us back but one?
闭嘴老太婆 如果老天听到了 说不定又多带走一个呢!
Quiet, woman, or heaven will hear you and take even him away.
谢谢 老表 这可是天大的好消息啊
Thank you, cousin.This news lightens our heavy hearts.
孙子可是大事啊
A grandson is no small thing.
按理说 小玉的孩子又不是你们的
By rights, this child of Jade's is not yours.
你个疯婆子乱说话
You talk with no thought.
别在意 老表 她最近受罪太多了
Pray excuse her. Bitterness has turned her words to gall.
如果小玉当初嫁给我们家儿子...
Had Jade married my son as she ought...
我儿子也不会死
...he would be alive today and safe there with her.
这样一来 小玉儿子才是我们的孙子
And so before the gods,her child is our grandchild.
我是不是应该把你轰出去
I should drive you from my house...
但是我可不想坏了我的心情
...but it would soil this moment.
这个难得的好心情
This joyful moment.
敌人们挡不住耕种的季节
But not even the enemy could stop the seasons.
春耕到了
And at last it was spring.
鬼子们发放种子给村民 不是让吃的 而是用来播种的
And each farmer was given grain.Not to eat, but to plant.
每颗种子 都是数过的
And it was said that each seed was counted...
如果种子没长 都要被追究
... and the man would answer for it if each seed did not yield.
老凌头只能像牛一样 背起缰绳开始犁地
So Ling Tan harnessed himself to his plow like an ox.
他跟老婆子一起 累到晕头转向的 分不清天地
And together, he and his old woman felt the earth turn beneath their feet.
虽然谷子长得又高又长
The grain grew straight and tall.
但是凌谭两口子没法像往常一样 高兴起来 ...
But Ling Tan and his wife could no longer take pleasure in it's promise...
他们知道 收成都不归他们自己的
... for they knew that what they worked for would not be theirs.
老婆子啊 你还没嫌鬼子们家里翻得底朝天啊
Now what, old woman? Has the enemy not done enough damage to my house?
你咋就有开始挖地洞了啊
Must you dig up the foundations?
我们必须把种子跟蔬菜藏起来啊
We will keep our seed and the vegetables we grow...
放在这个洞里面
...and hide them in this hole.
- 我都把洞挖的跟一头猪那么大了  - 啥猪
- I will make it big enough to hold a pig. - What pig?
你从鬼子那里偷的那头
The one you'll steal from the enemy's breeding farm.
那自然要更大一点啊
But it will have to be big.
您自己一个人怎么挖洞呢 这地太硬了
How can you dig such a thing without help. The earth is stubborn.
老天给我的点子 老天也会找个人来帮我的吧
Heaven gave me the thought. Heaven will provide the help.
铲子在那边
The shovel is there.
我们还得瞒着鬼子从自己的地里头偷点吃的
We will steal food from ourselves and eat it.
我刚听到你这么说的时候 还吓了一跳呢
I am too just a man to deny sense even to a woman, when I hear it from her.
要是所有人都这么干 鬼子们迟早变成狗尾巴上的跳蚤
If all do this, we'll harry the enemy like fleas in a dog's tail.
对对对 说不定他们还会停下来舔舔自己的狗屁股呢
And it may be that he will make little headway for stopping to gnaw at his rear.
- 爹  - 儿子
- My son. - My father.
真高兴见到你们
Oh, what gladness.
娘
My mother.
我孙子呢 他在哪 他在哪
Have I no grandson? Where is he? Where is he?
安静点 老太婆 你都没叫 鬼子们就能听到啦
Quiet, woman. Before you burst, and the enemy hears the sound you make.
你把我的乖孙子放哪里了
Where have you left my little dumpling?
又是书啊 书的 你会把我孙子压坏的
Books, still books. You've crushed him beneath them.
你爱书都胜过你自己儿子了
You seem to love them more than you love your child.
他闻起来真香
How sweet his flesh smells.
把灯挪近一点 我仔细瞧瞧
Bring the lamp close so I can see him.
我的乖孙子啊
Oh, my little meat dumpling.
看看这身板子 这头发 跟黑缎子一样
Oh, how firm he is of body, and his hair like black silk.
就跟我当初想的一模一样啊
He's exactly as I thought he would be.
我就知道你们会把孙子带回来给我看看的
I knew you'd bring him back to me. I knew. I knew.
不然我怎么活下去啊
Else I could not have lived.
每天每夜 我都在想着我的乖孙子啊
Night after night,I've dreamed of holding him like this.
悠着点 老太婆 悠着点
Guard you heart, old woman. Guard your heart.
是啊娘 别高兴过头了啊
Yes, my mother, too much joy is as bad as too much sorrow.
来 娘 喝茶 这样好说话
Here, my mother, drink down this cold tea.Then the words can come out.
你看 这可不是一般人的小孩啊 这脸 多方正啊
Why, this is no usual child.Look at his face, how square it is.
嘴巴也方正
And he has a square mouth.
- 来来来 把孙子还给我  - 你等会 老太婆 再等会
- Now give him back to me. - In a moment, old woman. In a moment.
我们这样过日子 鬼子能拿我们怎么样啊
What can the enemy do to us when our family goes on like this?
孙子回家咯 来来来吃点东西啊
There, now.You are in your home and you must eat.
娘 你等一下别急
I beg you not be angry with me, Mother...
但是你不要把嘴里的东西给小孩子吃
...but do not put food from your mouth into the child's.
我也是这么喂孩子的 没事的
Well, I fed my own son so. It did him no harm.
不是啦 现在不好 我带了一本育儿的书
But it is not thought good now. I bought a book and it told how to care for children.
- 书里说这样做是不对的 - 你这么一说 那你还是把孩子抱回去
- And it spoke against such things. - Why, you better take your child back.
- 我抱着他 他就给弄脏啦 - 娘 我只是为了把孙子带给你瞧瞧
- Doubtless, I pollute him when I hold him. - Mother, it was for you I brought him home.
别斗嘴了你们俩 今晚是个开心的日子啊
Cool your anger, both of you.Should we quarrel this night, of all nights...
他才是我们今晚的甜心啊
...and over the child who is the center of our hearts?
我养儿子的时候哪里看过什么书啊
Did I ever have a book to feed my children?
也没见我弄丢过儿子啊
Did I ever lose a son?
随她怎么做啦 她开心就行拉
Indulge her with the child. It will heal her for everything.
我们家有变得有生机了 老头子
Our house has come alive again, old man.
- 早上好 伙计  - 早上好
- Good day, friends. - Good day.
我儿子带来了指挥部的通知
My son comes from the free land. He has a message from the high command.
村子里到处都有像我一样的游击队员
There are many like me and we spread among the villagers...
告诉大伙应该怎么反抗敌人
...to tell such men as you what we must do.
我们必须打倒敌人
This enemy must be resisted.
解放区是公开的事情 而在占领区却是进行地下行动
Openly where the land is free and secretly where the land is lost.
我们必须秘密地进行斗争 比其他人还要任重道远
We, who must resist secretly, have a harder task than the others.
我们必须团结一致 一致对外
We must work togetheras the fingers on one hand.
我们必须监视敌人的行动 然后逐个击破
We must track down this enemy and kill him.
那我们应该这么做...
What we should do is this...
加入游击队 你这是要我们去送死啊
Join with the hill men? You're inviting us to die.
是的 死的像条汉子 而不是砧板上的猪头
Yes, but to die like men, not sheep on the butchering block.
你不要责备表叔啊
You must not blame our cousin.
读书人都是这样子畏手畏脚的
A scholar can never be as brave as one unlettered.
我们必须在爹的房子里面挖一个洞做暗室
We must build the hole under my father's house into one strong room.
好让游击队的同志躲在里面
And there we will hide the men that must be hidden.
你们哪里找的枪 上面还有洋文呢
Where did you find these guns? Some have foreign writing on them.
聪明的人都不问太多问题的
A wise man does not question a gift too closely.
我现在得去站岗了
I will take the guard now.
先吃点东西先 我还不累
No, eat first. I am not weary.
有个乡亲想知道我们怎么弄到枪的
One of our kinsmen wants to know where you found the guns.
你就说很容易弄到手的 只要用刀捅到鬼子肚子里面 就抢到了
Tell him they are easiest found by sticking a knife into the belly of an enemy soldier:
这枪给你 刚从鬼子的肚子里头拿出来的
And there is the gun for you, as if from his insides.
儿子们
My sons, all my sons.
我一个女人家能插什么话呢
What more can I ask, who am only a woman?
听听老三说的 看来他喜欢杀鬼子了
To hear our third son speak, one would think he'd like to kill.
不不不 你看看他 没事
Oh, how well he looks.
这些事情都跟我无关 我只负责做饭
And not on my cooking. I do not understand it.
娘 你要知道 现在好多女孩子仰慕老三呢
Oh, you should see the women admire him now.
- 不过呢 他都看不上眼   - 女人啊
- And still he has yet to choose one.- Women.
别自以为是
Do not turn your nose toward heaven.
你也是时候带个儿媳妇回家了 你多留心点
It's time you brought home a daughter-in-law. See that you do.
没有女人照料 我们会变成什么啊
What would become of us if we did not have the women to keep at us?
没有女人 也就没有你们这几个龟儿子
If you had no women,none of you would be born.
我死之前还想多抱一个孙子呢
I want grandsons before I die.
让吴连胖子去给你生一个去
Let fat men like Wu Lien bother with such nonsense.
我要专心打仗 这就是我现在想做的
I'm lean enough to fight. That is what I'm going to do.
我想知道 吴连现在如何了
I wanted to ask, what news of Wu Lien?
他全家都呆在城里受到鬼子保护 我是这么听说的
He and his family live in the city and are protected, I heard.
是的我也听说了 但是没听他们亲口告诉我们过
Yes, we have heard, but they haven't come to tell us so themselves.
吴连现在连他娘的坟墓都不敢来祭拜
Nor has Wu Lien been here to his mother's grave.
我也听说过这些人的事情
I have known of others who are protected.
难道他做了鬼子的走狗了
Could this mean he deals with the enemy?
- 我不相信 除非我真的见到了  - 我也不相信
- I will not believe that until I know it is so.- Nor will I.
有人来了
Someone comes.
是老沈 站岗的
It is Neighbor Shen, the lookout.
鬼子进村了
Enemy soldiers are in the village.
他们来抓壮丁了
They look for young men to slave for them.
好啊 我们来会会这些抓壮丁的鬼子们
Well, then, let us help them find what they seek.
- 来了多少鬼子  - 一整排 从这儿到村口那么多
- How many of the enemy? - A line from here to the door.
乡亲们 操家伙了
Kinsman, come out and bring enough guns...
大伙一起并肩作战
...for the others who will act with us.
这才刚刚开始呢
This is the beginning of it, then.
- 你能照顾好自己吗 - 不怕 让罗圈腿的鬼子们来吧
- You will be safe? - Let them come, the bandy-legs.
滚进车里
Get into the cart.
这些中国猪不会打仗的
These Chinese pigs do not fight.
他们生下来就是奴隶
They were born to be slaves.
不过这个蛮壮的
But this one is strong.
是啊 一头强壮的猪好干活
Yes, a good work animal.
这个送去挖矿更好 今晚收获不错啊
This one will be sent to the mine. We made a good catch tonight.
小菜一碟啊
This is almost too easy.
把其他人带上车
Bring the rest to the cart.
这些人都是我要找的
They're the ones I found.
全他妈的是干活的牲口
We need more work animals like this.
再搜搜那些房子
Search the houses again.
估计还有些躲起来了
Some of them are still hiding.
谁反抗就毙了谁
Shoot any that resist.
我们得教教他们如何效忠天皇陛下
We must teach them that it is an honor to serve the emperor.
- 拦住他! - 抓住他!
- Stop him. - Catch him.
如果他跑了 我们的计划就暴露了 他会带更多鬼子来杀我们
If he escapes, we are lost. He will bring others to kill us.
- 别开枪 别开枪  - 别怕 鬼子
- Don't shoot. Don't shoot. - Do not be afraid.
我不开枪 我他妈捅死你
I am not going to shoot you.
- 睡觉吧 老头子  - 还是说你要站着睡
- Come to bed, old man. - Or have you learned to sleep standing up?
小玉不是读过一本书
The name of the book that Jade once read...
叫 我们都是兄弟姐妹 吗
...was it not All Men Are Brothers?
是啊 这本书把你吵得睡不着吗
It was. But is that something to steal your rest?
不是不是
This is what troubles me.
小玉跟老二怎么能这样杀人呢 如果所有人都是兄弟姐妹的话
How can Jade send forth her husband to kill other men if all men are his brothers?
可能是因为那些鬼子都不是人 而是禽兽
Perhaps because the bandy-legs are no longer men but beasts.
但是我们会不会也变成杀人的畜生呢
But must we, too, become as beasts?
今晚我看到人们用不同的方式杀人
Tonight, I learned that men kill differently.
我看到老三把刀子通到鬼子肚子里头
I saw our third son with his knife and...
他回到家里
He came back into this house...
用沾满鲜血的手抓东西吃
...and picked up food and ate it
with the blood still upon his hands.
我觉得那样不对
I say that is wrong.
但是鬼子还在呢 我们要不杀他们 要不被他们杀
Yet the enemy is upon us. We must kill them or be killed.
但是有件事情我们要记住 说不定我们的人也会自相残杀的
But there is one thing we must remember, old woman, or we have killed ourselves too.
和平才是对的
Peace is good.
年轻人可能都忘了
The young cannot remember it.
但是我们都记得
And it is we who must remember...
应该让儿孙们知道 和平才是最好的精神食粮
...and teach them again that peace is man's great food.
你要是再生多一个儿子的话 你就不用自己动手了
If you had two sons,there would be no work done.
有人来了
Someone comes.
是你们家大姐
It is only your elder sister.
- 别告诉别人我们来过 娘  - 我们进去屋里头藏起来
- Do not tell them we are here, Mother. - We will go to the hidden room.
这年头 真是怪事啊连姐弟都不能相见
This is a strange day when brothers and sisters hide from each other.
现在每天都有怪事发生
All days are strange now.
有鬼子
Soldiers.
好像很有钱的样子
They look rich.
鬼子都这么肥头大耳吗
Were they always so fat?
可能我们看习惯了皮包骨头的人了吧
Perhaps our eyes have grown used to people afraid and hungry.
长辈们 我们来看你们了
My old ones, here we are to see you.
真是万幸啊
A thousand fortunes.
我想你们过的挺好的嘛
I trust you are well.
欢迎我们进去屋里坐一坐吗
Are we then welcome to come within?
你们全家都是受欢迎的
You and your family are welcome.
不过其他人我就不欢迎了
But I cannot let others into my house.
别担心 这些只是我的守卫
You need not fear.
These two only came to guard me.
在我家 不用守卫
What guard do you need in my house?
我家老丈人比较胆小
My father-in-law is old and afraid.
我不胆小 但是我就是不想让他们进来
I'm not afraid. But I will not have them in my house.
那我就只能在外头守着了
Then I must wait here with the guards.
- 你能给几个凳子坐吗 爹  - 可以
- Will you bring stools to sit upon? - I will.
乡巴佬 真粗鲁
Country people, they have no manners.
我弟弟们呢
Where, then, are my brothers?
他们都逃难去了 就剩下我们俩了
They are gone, and we are alone.
你大哥的孩子也死了
Even your elder brother's children are dead.
不是饿死就是病死
They died of sickness and starvation.
世道不好啊
It is the times.
我替我大哥感到难过 你也节哀啊 娘 我也担心你
I grieve for my elder brother and for you also. I weep for you.
别多心了 我眼泪早就流干了
Do not waste your tears. My own have dried.
你为什么这么倔
Why are you so stiff?
你要知道 我做的一切可都是精打细算啊
You must know that what I do is done only for the best.
我哪里知道你都干了些什么呢
I do not know what you do.
识时务者为俊杰啊 机会是给有准备的人啊
Times are times, and the wise man takes his time as he finds it.
有时候 妥协比勇敢要实用很多
Compromise is sometimes better than valor.
你们现在住在哪里
Where do you live now?
北门街10号
At the 10th house of the North Gate Street.
那可是有钱人的房子啊 你们怎么住进去的
That is a street of fine houses. How can you live there?
我是被请过去的 我替新政府工作的
I am told to live there.I work for the new government.
待遇又好 我也高兴
I'm well-paid and I'm content.
你明白我的意思吗 岳父
You see what I would say, my father-in-law?
我是个粗人 听不懂
I am a common man. I am so stupid...
我只听得懂人话 从人嘴巴里面说出来的
...I understand only a thing when it is said to me, and when I hear it.
我今天可是来帮你的 岳父
I come here today to help you.
如果你按我说的做 你的日子会好过很多的
If you do as I say, your life will be easier.
- 那我应该做些什么呢  - 按我吩咐的去做就可以了
- What must I do? - Do whatever is told you to do.
我会随时联络你
And I will manage for you here and there as I'm able.
你现在又都做些什么事情呢 女婿
What had you to do, son-in-law?
只有一件事 我负责帮皇军进货
For one thing, I'm a controller of all incoming goods.
大米啊 小麦啊 鱼啊 鸦片啊 盐啊什么的...
Rice and wheat, fish, opium, salt...
鸦片 鸦片 那鬼东西害得多少中国人生不如死你知道吗
Opium? Opium? That evil was driven from our country by great pain and suffering.
- 你现在还敢把它弄回来卖  - 我自己也做不了主啊
- And now you bring it back. - But I'm not my own master.
你们怎么这么铁石心肠啊
How can you be so hard?
毕竟家里就剩下你们两口子了
After all, there are only you two old people left.
- 我们现在就是你们唯一的亲人了  - 别瞎操心 我们死不了
- And we are all you have. - We can live.
我们最好走吧 这里容不下我们
You do well to leave. We are not wanted here.
看来我们儿子的担心是对的
What our son feared was true.
诅咒这帮狗东西
Curse this enemy.
害得我跟我女儿吵架了
He has made me quarrel with my daughter.
瞧瞧 吴连那家人现在好吃好穿 还有鬼子帮
See? Silk coats and enemy soldiers to serve him.
看样子吴连捞了很大一笔油水啊
It is plain Wu Lien has got his fingers into the fat.
有钱又如何 你又不去巴结他
Of what value is a rich relative unless you can put him to use?
我们是吴连的亲戚 想见见吴连
We are his kinsmen and would see Wu Lien.
进去吧 吴连欢迎你们
Go in. Wu Lien sees anybody.
请问吴连的房间在哪里
Where are the rooms of Wu Lien, our rich relative?
那里
In there.
还有什么比亲戚拜访更让人开心的事情么
What greater pleasure is there than a short visit from relatives?
来就来嘛 不用带什么鱼啊什么的 留着自己吃就是啊
But next time, eat the fish. Do not bring it to us.
吴连 你真是个大好人
Wu Lien, you're a kind, good man.
你就不能给我们家糟老头
Can you not find my old man a worthless little piece of work...
在这个大房子里面安排个小差事吗
...here in these walls to pay us something?
我岳父应该不会赞成他过来这边吧
But will my father-in-law let him come here?
我老公不用他管 再怎么说
My husband by right should have more power than your father-in-law...
他辈分更高 更有权力
...because he is older. And it is time he took that power.
你也这样认为吗 表叔
Do you think the same way, elder cousin?
- 我老公跟我是想到一块的   - 然后呢
- My husband always thinks as I do. - And how's that?
我觉得我们得为了自己
I think we must save ourselves at all cost...
为了自己的将来着想
...and bow before what is upon us...
好好计划一下
...and do what we can to make something of it.
也是 不过你们呆在村子里面会更好一点
Yes, perhaps you will be more content to remain in the village...
那里毕竟有更多你们认识的人
...where you are known and know everybody.
不过这里也时刻欢迎你们 我们会给你们吃的 还有钱
But you are welcome to visit us here. We'll give you food, money.
不过你们得给我一些情报
And then you can give us the news.
我们知道的很少的 小村子那有什么情报啊
We have very little to tell. Nothing happens in our village.
吴连啊 最近村子里面发生很多事情
Much has happened and more will. Wu Lien.
我老头子跟我都愿意当你的耳目
My old man and I will be as one eye and one ear.
我们的所见所闻 都会通通告诉你
And all that we see and hear, you shall see and hear also.
我们一直很想知道你们在做些什么 还有我的岳父岳母
We always like to hear how you do, and my wife's father and mother.
- 还有他们的几个儿子 - 当然当然
- And her brothers also? - Of course, of course.
他们也是我们亲戚
They are also our kin.
但是他们走了之后 好像就没什么消息了
But since they are away,there must be little news of them.
是的是的 他们去了解放区 没在家
True, true, they're all in the free land and not at home.
难道我看到的小玉跟她的胖儿子是在梦里看见的
Then perhaps I saw Jade and her fat child in a dream.
小玉有儿子了
Oh, Jade has a child, then?
是的是的 信里面说的
Yes, yes, the news came in a letter from the free land.
- 我们也没看到过  - 小玉的胖儿子长得可好呢
- But we've not seen the child. - Child is a fine boy. Too fine.
那胖娃儿命硬 每次我看到他的时候...
Death sits on his eyebrows, I say,whenever I look at him...
我都看到过好几次呢
...which is often.
你这里环境不错啊 表亲 你的差事一定很不错
You live well here, cousin.Your position must be good.
表面风光 里头又是另外一回事
It is smooth on the top but under it is another thing.
皇军最近很不好伺候 说不定会把我们给撤了
Our conquerors feel a rising anger that may engulf us all.
为什么会这样
How then?
许多士兵从城市里面运来食物跟货物
Too many soldiers have gone forth from the city for food and goods...
但是都有去无返回
...and have not returned.
连尸首都找不到
Not even their bodies have been found.
太莫名其妙了 这样下去的话会毁掉我们大家的饭碗的
It is a great mystery, and one that may destroy all of us.
甚至牵连你们这些无辜的人
Even the innocent.
现在我必须向你坦白
Now, now, I will speak and fully.
鬼子们看样子已经知道村子里面杀人的事情了
The enemy is sure to find out that the killing started in our village.
这样我们也自身难保
Then what will our lives be worth?
吴连 这事情跟我们没关系 是老凌家干的
Wu Lien, we had nothing to do with it. It is Ling Tan.
凌谭跟他的儿子们 他们全都回来了 还跟游击队一起
Ling Tan and his sons. They are all returned and work with the hill men.
- 我亲眼看到过他们 他们都是头目  - 这女人都瞎了 疯掉了
- I've seen them and they are the leaders. - The woman's blind as a mole and crazy.
就算瞎了,也知道敌人被杀死然后埋在了...
Not too blind to see enemy dead piled in the streets and buried...
老凌家的暗室里面 那里还有许多枪支跟游击队呢
...in the hidden room beneath Ling Tan's house where men and guns are.
虽然 有些年轻人死了 我儿子就是其中过一个
Yes, other young men have died, my son among them.
但是偏偏不是老凌家的儿子
But not the sons of Ling Tan.
而且 他们现在还在得意的大吹大擂
No, they still spit and stride about and boast.
娘们 你怎么能这样诬陷老凌一家呢
Woman, how can you utter such lies against Ling Tan?
他们家对我们一向很好 一直救济我们啊
He has been good to us. He has fed us often.
- 你怎么能忘记这些呢  - 我全他妈忘记了
- Can you forget this? - I can forget it.
就他那点小恩小惠 就以为了不起
He likes to give us small gifts. It makes him bigger in his own eyes.
- 我们还要感恩戴德吗  - 我没看出来他这么说过啊
- Shall we thank him for his own pride? - I'm not concerned with his pride.
- 我自己还有点自尊  - 你是有一堆自尊 我看着呢
- I'd rather have some of my own. - And you shall have. I will see to it.
只有当你有的吃有的穿
When you wear a silk coat over a full round belly...
你才有那么一点点的自尊
...you will have pride in yourself then.
你口口声声的自尊跟我所说的
What use to speak to you of pride when we use the same word...
是同一个意思吗
...but mean different things by it?
你真他妈的不是一个男人
Of all men on earth, you are least like a man.
- 别担心那老头  - 好的
- Do not worry about that one. - Yes.
他会听我的话的 放心
He will follow me, or answer to me.
我们随时欢迎你 我的亲戚
We will always be glad to see you, kinswoman.
改天我们再聊 找一个安静的地方我们好好聊聊就是
Another time? Another quiet little talk such as this one has been.
好的好的 我会给你好消息的
Yes. Yes, as soon as we have fresh news.
我爹全家看起来走了一条万劫不复的路
My poor father and his household walk on a rope above a pit.
我已经忘记刚刚表婶说的事情了
I have forgotten the things we have heard.
你呢 老公
Have you, my husband?
我可不这么认为 我记得很清楚呢
No, I have a mind that lets go of nothing.
佐藤上尉找你
Captain Sato calls for you.
- 他吩咐带上你手头的工作 - 好的好的 马上马上
- He says, bring the work you have finished. - Oh, yes, yes. Yes, at once.
中国人欢迎他们的好邻居
The Chinese people welcome their good neighbor...
给他们吃的 保护他们
...who gives them food, peace and safety.
- 做的不错嘛  - 谢谢夸奖
- It is a clever work. - Thank you.
说不定这事儿可以帮我们避免一些无谓的伤亡呢
And perhaps it will help us to put an end to all these killings.
我会去四处转帖这些海报的
I will put the poster in all the usual places.
中国佬!
Chinaman!
过来
Come here.
我不是派你去收集...
Did I not instruct you to obtain information for me...
- 有关那些士兵失踪情报吗 - 太君 我...
- ...about the disappearance of our soldiers? - Sir, I...
我还没找到有用的情报
I have found nothing as yet.
你不觉得那个村子就是游击队的老窝吗
Do you think that one village is the center of this rebellion?
如果是的话 我们应该怎么找呢
And if it is, how can we find it?
或许我们应该烧掉所有的房子 杀死所有的村民
and shoot all the farmers.
这样还会有人刚反抗皇军吗
Will that end this stupid resistance?
但是这样的话 太君 这样的话
Perhaps, sir. Perhaps, but then...
来年怎么找人去种播种收割啊
...who would plant and harvest the crop next year if you did that?
如果没有了收成 士兵就没饭吃啊
And if there was no crop,how could your army here be fed?
- 你们吃饭也会成问题了啊 太君  - 我们知道 中国佬
- How would you yourselves eat, great ones? - We thought of that, Chinaman.
我们只是想知道 你是不是也明白这一点
We only wondered if you had also.
- 既然我们有这个共识  - 是的 太君
- And so we are all agreed. - Yes, great one.
我们都认为我们必须找到游击队的老窝
We are agreed that we must find that center.
- 然后消灭他们 - 是的 太君
- And destroy it. - Yes, great one.
- 你也必须协助我们   - 好的 谢谢
- And it will be your privilege to help us. - Thank you.
我很快就会有消息的 如果可能的话 很快就会知道的
I will have information soon. If it is possible, very soon.
谢谢
Thank you.
没有汉奸 我们怎么占领这个国家呢
How could we conquer a country without its traitors?
他们让我去逗士兵笑
They order me to broaden the smile on the face of the soldier.
难道他们不知道我是在虎口拔牙吗
Do they not know a broader smile will only make him resemble a shark the more?
你没告诉他们关于我老家的事情吧
You did not speak of your new knowledge?
没有
I did not.
你会不会说出去
Will you ever speak of it?
只要我能 我尽量不说
As long as I am able, I will not.
但是万一你不能呢 然后会不会呢
But when you are no longer able,what then?
我怎么知道啊
How can I tell that?
我怎么知道明天自己会怎样做啊
How does a man know today what he must do tomorrow?
你怕了 你现在进退两难了
You are afraid. You are in danger here.
我什么时候不进退两难?
Where am I not in danger?
这个年代 谁还敢跟豺狼虎豹住在一起啊
In these times, one chooses to live in the den of the tiger or the lion.
也没有其他地方了
There is no other place.
我只是墙头草而已
And I am a man in the middle.
怎么可能不会动摇呢
How can a man in the middle stay there without splitting himself?
如果这样的话 那就危险了
And if he does that, he is only half a man.
谁都可能随时要了我的命啊
Half. Can half a man still live?
三表弟啊
Here is our third cousin.
你还好吧 老表
How are you, cousin?
怎么啦
What is it?
我就应该把我老婆给掐死
I should have killed her even as she spoke.
你想掐死谁
Who would you kill then?
我家老婆子
The female I call my wife.
她哪里又惹你了
Has that woman been snapping at your heels again?
我要是能掐死她 我自己也会死了算了
Had I killed her, I myself would have been killed...
这样村子就安全了
...but at least our village would now be safe...
乡亲们也没事了
...and all our kinsmen.
发生什么事了 表叔
What is this, cousin?
我坦白告诉你们
This is not easy for me to say but I must.
我老婆是个叛徒
My wife is a traitor.
她把所有事情都告诉吴连了
She has told Wu Lien all she knows of what happens here.
包括暗室 还有你们儿子跟游击队的事情
Of the secret room and your sons and the resistance.
吴连 这个走狗
Wu Lien, the running dog.
他必须保密
He must be silenced.
但是说不定他会说出去的
But he may not speak.
还有另外一个人可能会说出去的
There is another who has already spoken and may do so again...
三表婶
...the wife of our cousin here.
不会的相信我 她不会说出去的
I can say only this. She will speak no more.
你杀死她了
You have killed her.
没有 我狠狠揍了她一顿 揍到她刚刚...
No, no, I did not kill her. Although there was a moment...
都差点没气了
..when I thought she no longer breathed.
我揍啊揍
I beat her.
揍到她站都站不起来
I beat her until she leaned against the wall to keep from falling.
那吴连怎么办
What then of Wu Lien?
他至少是我们家的一份子啊
We must remember this:He is of our family.
我们儿子今晚可就要崇从山里回来的呀
Our sons return from the hills tonight.
他们知道怎么抓住他的啊 村里只有一条回来的路
They will know how to deal with him. There is but one way.
我丈夫会跟我想到一块的 而且这件事情我们必须做
I know my husband will see it as I see it and be willing to do what must be done.
你们打算杀死你们姐夫
Would you have him kill his brother-in-law?
总比被姐夫杀死好吧
Rather than have his brother-in-law kill him.
我自己没办法决定
I cannot decide this alone.
来吧 老表
Come, cousin.
这可关系到全村老小啊
It concerns us all in the village.
如果天下和平了 一切还会是变回老样子吗
Can anything ever be the same again even though peace comes?
没了这些小事情 我就是大老爷们一个了
Some small good has come of this.Out of it, I am born a man again.
我必须进城
I must go to the city.
我从你眼睛里看出来了
I read what you would do in your eyes.
- 你站在我一边吗 娘  - 我跟你站一边
- You are with me on this, Mother? - I am with you, Daughter.
男人开会的时候 我们女人就开始行动了
Women ever must act while men waste time in talk.
一点点这个东西
The great power of this...
无色无味 杀人无形
...is that a grain kills in a second
and is as tasteless as flour.
最近很多女人买这个东西
Many women buy this poison in these times.
多数给自己 也有给别人的
Some for themselves and some for others.
你需要多少
How much will you need?
我自己可能不需要了 我相信我也用不着
I may not need any at all.I hope I do not.
但是我今天能买 我就多买一些
But I will take as much as I have money to buy.
吴连在吗
Wu Lien?
小玉 怎么是你啊
Jade. It cannot be.
你好啊 大姐 姐夫呢
How are you, sister-in-law?
房子的守卫不错啊
This house is well-guarded.
我一说我是你们亲戚 他们就让我进来了
But when I told them I was your relative, the gate opened like magic.
他们站自己岗而已 不针对你大姐夫的
Yes, they guard themselves, but not against my husband.
你为什么这样看着我 见到我不高兴吗
Why do you stare so at me? Are you not glad to see me?
不是不是 我很高兴
Yes. Yes, I am glad.
看起来你气色不错啊 除了瘦一点
You look well, if not fat.
我还没有时间休息呢 昨天刚从解放区回来
I have not rested yet. I returned from the free land only yesterday.
- 昨天  - 我的丝绸上衣呢
- Only yesterday? - Where's my silk coat, I...
小玉来看我们了 她昨天刚刚回啦
Here is Jade to see us. She tells me she returned but yesterday.
我跟我老公儿子一起回来的 他们现在还在睡觉呢
Together with my husband and son. And today, they still sleep.
欢迎欢迎 弟妹 很高兴看到你们回来
Welcome, sister-in-law,we're glad you are home again.
二老两个人孤独太久了
The old ones have been too long alone.
- 我的上衣呢  - 这里 可以穿了
- Now, where is my coat? - Here it is. Ready for you to wear.
我老公今晚要参加皇军的一个聚会
My husband will be honored tonight at a banquet for the conquerors.
是的 我得赶紧去穿衣服先
Yes, and now I must dress for it.
我们两个女人说话不影响你吧 姐夫
Will not our women's prattle disturb him?
不会不会 我听不到的
Oh, no, no. I will not hear it.
我穿过城里的时候 看到一些不一样的地方
As I came through the city, I found many changes.
我老公说 皇军很高兴看到...
My husband says the conqueror prides himself...
他做得一些群众工作
...on the public improvements he has made.
群众工作
Improvements?
我看到士兵在贴海报
Today, I saw enemy soldiers pasting up a picture...
上面画着日本鬼子笑着发放食物给..
...which showed another enemy soldier smiling and giving food to our people...
跪在地上的人们
...who knelt before him.
那是我老公画的 画看起来还不错吧
That is my husband's handiwork. Is it not good to look upon?
还可以
Very.
那张画下面的人
Beneath the picture and looking up at it stood hungry people.
正端着碗
And they brought bowls and crept close...
偷偷得把画下面的浆糊抠下来
...and scooped up some of the paste that the soldiers were using.
然后吃掉
And then they ran away and hid and ate it.
吃浆糊
Ate the paste?
总比饿死好啊
Even that is better than nothing.
但是皇军发粮食的啊
But the conqueror does give food.
我们有拿到的啊 其他人也应该有啊
He gives it to us and there must be others.
是的 也会啊
Yes, there are others.
鬼子也给孩子们吃糖
The enemy sometimes gives sweets, and often to children.
至少这件事情不是什么坏事啊
Well, then, you must admit that giving sweets to children is not evil.
不是坏事 里面可是有鸦片啊
Is it not? In the sweets is opium.
小孩子们一旦吃下去 浑身血管就像着火一样
When once the children eat it, they have the hunger that is fire in their veins.
一辈子就彻底毁掉了
And so they are spoiled forever.
你家小孩看起来就很好
Your own children look well.
日本话学的很快嘛 这小孩
He has learned the tongue of the enemy very quickly.
谁知道长大了会不会变成日本人呢
Who knows what he may grow up to say in it.
我们会用自己的东西教好他们的
We will remember our own things to tell him.
别忘了告诉他们其他小孩发生的事情
Then do not forget to tell him of the other children.
还有那些小孩子父母的遭遇
And the mothers and fathers of those children...
他们都被绑在一起 泡在汽油里面
...all tied together and soaked with oil.
活活被烧死 无论他们怎么哀求
And burned alive while they cried for mercy.
我不想再听到这些事情了
I will hear no more of this. All the killing.
告诉你老婆别怕 姐夫
Tell your wife not to shudder,brother-in-law.
这些事情 每天都在发生
People now take these as things that may happen to any one of us.
- 每天都有  - 我得先去喝口茶
- And any day. - I will get tea.
我希望自己没有打扰到你们 姐夫
I trust I did not disturb you.
我听说的事情不多
I heard very little.
你是不是也变得麻木不仁无 动于衷了啊
Can it be that you have trained your ears not to hear what you do not wish to hear?
你...
You...
你得原谅你大姐 她只是一个普通女人 跟我们不一样
You must forgive my wife. She is but a woman and not as we are.
我从来不认为我们是一路人
I do not think we are the same.
我想你是在跟我们这些人作对
I think you are against me and all who are with me.
我不跟任何人作对
I am against no one.
那你支持我们吗
Are you for us, then?
我不支持也不反对
I'm neither for nor against anything.
你不支持就是反对
What you are not for, you are against.
你去了解放区 人就变了
You have changed while you were away in the free land.
我可不知道这样的变化对于你而言好不好
I'm not sure the change becomes you.
不 不 不好
No. No, it does not.
女人就应该柔情万种
A woman should be soft, like the skin of a peach.
而不是铁石心肠 这样对谁都不好
Not hard like the stone which does no one any good.
你可别忘了 石头里面才能长出大树的
Do not forget that the tree itself grows from the stone.
那可是万物开始地方
Surely that is the beginning of everything.
我要是能偶尔看看爹娘 我就很知足了
If I could see my parents sometimes I would be content.
你老公很知足 我觉得你应该也是啊 大姐
Your husband is content and so must you be.
是的 我就是这样 我老婆也是
Yes, I am what I am. And so is my wife.
她总是恪守妇道
And she is one who has always known her place as a woman and kept to it.
你能帮我转达一下爹娘
Will you tell my parents this for me?
- 告诉他们我很挂念他们   - 会的会的 小玉会告诉他们的
- Will you tell them I think of them often? - Yes, she will tell them.
现在你去看看孩子是不是该喂了 我们还有事情要说
And now, if you wish to feed your children, we will excuse you.
你不跟我一起喝喝茶吗 姐夫
Will you not share some tea with me, brother-in-law...
虽然我一介女流
...although I am only a woman?
来吧 我帮你倒茶
Come, I will pour it for you.
不用不用 不麻烦你啦
No. Although I thank you.
我想东西的时候 吃不下东西的
I cannot eat when I have something on my mind to do.
我现在肚子饿得咕咕叫了
My stomach growls and takes offense.
那是那是 你怎么说也是一个很会审时度势的人啊
Surely you are a man who should nourish himself at every opportunity.
别担心我 我今晚会大吃一顿的
Do not worry about me. I will eat myself full tonight.
有烤鸭 我最喜欢吃烤鸭了
There is duck and I am very fond of duck.
请进请进
Oh, enter, enter.
大厨啊 一切都安排好了吧
Well, then, cook,I trust everything in the kitchen is well.
你喊我来 我就来了 别跟我废话了
You sent for me. I am here. Do not waste time on idle talk.
我喊你来是想知道...
Yes, I sent for you, but only to ask...
所有吃的是不是按照我的要求准备好了
...if the food will be prepared in fashion as I have ordered.
清蒸鸭子 香草母鸡
Steamed duck, pullets with Chinese herbs...
鸽子蛋汤 鱼翅蒸螃蟹
...pigeon eggs in soup, and shark's fins with crabmeat.
都准备好了 你太罗嗦了
All will be ready.You have too many words.
- 请务必确保所有东西都准备妥当  - 放心 都准备好了
- Be sure everything is ready... - It will be ready when it is ready.
- 我不喜欢被人催  - 好的好的
- I am not a man to be hurried. - Yes.
你看到了吧 我们有的是吃的 绰绰有余
You see, we have plenty of food here.More than enough.
- 你要不带点回去家里  - 不用了
- Will you not take some home with you? - No.
等等 为什么不呢 反正吃不完也得喂狗啊 为什么不拿一点呢
Oh, but why? It will only be thrown to the dogs. Why do you not take it?
因为我们不是狗 姐夫
Because, brother-in-law we are not dogs.
等一下 你不能进去 陌生人是不能进去的
Wait. You cannot enter. Strangers are not allowed in the kitchen.
这是谁啊
What is the...?
你们不是要请人吗
Did you not send for someone?
不是要个新厨子吗
A new cook, perhaps?
我不觉得你会做饭
Well, I would not think cooking is one of your talents.
你不试试怎么知道
How can you know that until you have tried me?
我把她轰到大街上
I will throw her into the street.
不用 我晚点亲自轰她出去
I will do that myself. Later, perhaps.
你们继续干活
Get on with your work.
你怎么来到这个房子的
How did you get into this house?
奇怪吗 吴连叫我来的
Is it not plain? Wu Lien sent for me.
吴连为什么叫你
Why?
噢 你不用回答 我看他老婆长得样子就知道怎么回事了
Oh, you need not answer.I have seen his wife.
该给猪抹油了 准备好
It is time to baste the pigs. Get them ready.
快点告诉我 为什么溜进来厨房
Now, tell me, why did you come into the kitchen, huh?
我饿了 我知道这里有吃的
I am hungry. There is food here.
那吴连为什么不给你啊
Why, did you not get food from Wu Lien?
吴连没记性 而且也不会一直给我吃的
Wu Lien will not last. He could not feed me for long.
我也不会给你吃的啊 中国人是不能进厨房的
Nor can I.Chinese are not allowed in the kitchen.
但是我不属于任何国家 我只是一个女人而已
But I am one who is of no country.I am only a woman.
我跟日本人在一起 难道你还要怪我吗
Can you blame me if I would be
with those who have conquered here?
- 这么说你喜欢我们咯 - 不 一点都不
- So you like us, then? - No, I do not.
但是我更不想挨饿
But I like hunger even less.
所以你不怕我们
Oh, so you're not afraid.
我这不捡大便宜了 找到一个不怕我们的女人
Can it be that I have found a woman of my own liking?
- 那你会给我吃的吗 - 吃的 东西很贵的
- You will feed me then? - Feed you? Food is dear.
你打算用什么付钱啊
How will you pay for it?
怎么付钱 我试试能不能帮忙在厨房做点事情
How? How else then to make myself useful?
做点事情 好的好的 我会让你做点事情的
Useful? Oh, yes, I will make you useful.
面条 来点面条 快点
Noodles, bring the noodles. Hurry.
你 把面条拿过来 快点
Here, you. You, bring the noodles, quick.
我忙着呢
I am busy.
离我远一点 等我做完了 我们就有得吃了
Stay out of my way until I finish my work.Then we shall eat.
然后我们一起慢慢吃
Yes, we shall eat together.
悄悄地一起吃
Alone and in private.
汤面 好了没有 来
Here. Soup noodles, are they ready? Come.
鸽子蛋呢
Where are the pigeon's eggs?
这是鱼
These are the fish.
还没好吗 该上菜了啊
Have you not finished yet? It's almost time to serve them.
鸭子不错 给鸭子浇点汁
Fine duck. Gravy. Gravy for the duck.
蘑菇呢 蘑菇在哪里
Mushrooms. Where are the mushrooms?
- 这个做得不够好  - 鱼
- These are not fine enough. - The fish.
面条 快一点 面条
Noodles. More noodles, hurry.
你个蠢货 别把汁烧焦了
You fool. Do not burn the sauce.
蟹肉 切好一点
The crabmeat. Cut it fine.
我都说了 滚开
I have said stay out of my way.
眼睛就只知道看着吃的 不看我
So you have eyes only for the food,not for me, huh?
你饿了吧 来来来 吃点鸭肉
Very well, if you are so greedy,take some of the duck.
来啊 吃啊
Go on, take it.
吃啊
Eat it.
滚滚滚 你要是真吃了 我就该掉脑袋了
No. No, little one, it would be my head if I were to let you have any of that.
上菜 趁热端上去给他们
Here, now, take these.Serve them while they're hot.
我跟你说啊 小宝贝
I have your own word for it, little one.
你越饥渴 我一会就越享受
The hungrier you are, the better it is for me.
清蒸鸭
Duck.
清蒸鸭来了 从里到外全是汁啊
Duck, swimming in its own juices.
我好不容易弄到的 特地按照你们的要求做的 太君
I went to great trouble to get them and have them cooked to your orders, sirs.
酒呢 吃鸭肉的酒呢
The wine for the duck, where is it?
酒?
Wine?
应该马上就来了 我刚刚喊了
Well, it will be served soon, I have ordered it.
- 那就再喊一次  - 是的 太君
- Order it again. - Yes, great one.
他都吓出汗了 虽然也是个中国佬
He sweats a great deal, even for a Chinese.
今晚我们再吓到他尿裤子
He will sweat even more tonight.
我们晚点跟他说正事的时候 再顺便抓弄一下他
We will amuse ourselves a little with him before we make him talk for us.
阁下 司令 将军 上尉 请用膳吧
Excellency, admiral, major, captain,please.
耐心点 小宝贝
Be patient, little one.
他们点了虾吗 来点新鲜的大虾
Now, they call these shrimp? I asked for fresh shrimp.
过来
Here now.
你吃完了才让你走
You would not be leaving before you have eaten.
我实在饿的不行了 我去别的地方吃去
I was weary of waiting. I would eat elsewhere.
- 不行 - 酒呢 酒呢
- You will not... - Where is the wine?
- 晚点上酒 我尽量... - 拦住那个女人!拦住她!
- The wine will come later. I am trying to... - That woman! Stop her. Stop her.
拦住她 那个女人 拦住她!
Stop her. That woman. Stop that woman.
别让她跑了 拦住她
Do not let her get away. Stop. Stop her.
- 你 你吓跑她了  - 她在厨房多久了
- You. You frightened her away. - How long has she been in this kitchen?
有什么所谓 这样的女人对你没什么好处
Why the difference? A woman like that is too good for you.
现在我们两人都没机会了
Now neither of us will have her.
她是不是
Was she...?
快叫守卫 快叫守卫!
Call the guard. Call the guard.
赶紧回家
Family.
快叫守卫
Call the guard.
中国佬!
Chinaman!
发生什么事啦
What is it?
鬼子...
The enemy...
被下毒了
...was poisoned.
他们怪罪到我身上
They blame me.
快去找你爹 带上孩子们 快
Go to your father. Take children. Quick.
- 快快  - 不 不 我不能
- Quick, quick. - No. No, I cannot.
谁干的
Who did this?
快走
Go.
乡亲们没有达成一致
Our kinsmen are not agreed among themselves.
有些人说杀了吴连
Some say kill Wu Lien at once.
我赞成杀了吴连 让我来杀都行
I say kill Wu Lien. Yes, kill him and let me do it.
老天爷会保佑我的 给我力量跟时间去干掉他
Heaven will lead me to the place and time and heaven will put power in my hand.
别老天这 老天那的
Do not say heaven this and heaven that.
如果我们要杀人 就别说是老天说的
If we kill, let us not say it is heaven who bids it.
互相残杀都不是老天的旨意
It is not heaven's will that men kill each other.
这我们知道 你就应该跟那些老不死的呆在一起
We know better. You lie dead with your ancestors...
- 而不是坐在这里  - 你怎么生出来这样的儿子啊
- ...instead of living. - How could you have borne such a son?
- 你不就是他爹吗  - 吴连怎么说也是我们家人啊
- How could you have fathered him? - Wu Lien is of our family.
我们只能希望他会顾虑这一点 而不会出卖我们
It is our one hope that he cannot bring himself to destroy us.
事到如今我们只能这样认为了
But we must be sure.
娘 娘 我是你女儿啊
My mother, my father,it is your daughter.
我去开门
I will go.
- 娘 娘!  - 怎么啦这是
-  Mother. Mother. - What is it?
吴连死了
My husband is dead.
有人在司令部的食物里面下毒
And so poison was put into the food of the high enemy officials by someone...
他们怪罪我丈夫 然后就把他杀了
...and they blamed my husband for it and killed him.
- 鬼子杀死他了   - 他们开枪杀了他
- The enemy killed him? - They shot him.
他在最后的快断气的时候跑回了家 让我快走
And he came to me holding the last of his life inside him with his hands.
他只是为了这个家啊 但是现在他死了
He lived only for his family, and now he is dead.
- 他多好一个人啊  - 我的希望落空了
- He was so good. - I have been cheated of my pleasure.
你今天也看到了啊 小玉 如今他都死了啊
You were there today, Jade. You saw him. And now he's dead.
我丈夫死了 我都成寡妇了
My husband is gone and I'm a widow.
女人是下毒的高手啊
Poison is a woman's weapon.
是的
Yes, it is.
是我干的
And it was I who used it.
我早知道了
I thought so.
我看到你跟娘在嘀咕着什么
I saw the look that passed between you and my mother.
你告诉我要坚定信念的
You said we must be sure.
我很坚定
I was sure.
他可能会告密 背叛我们全家
He would have betrayed us.
我没有打算杀他 也没打算让他死
I would not have killed him had I thought he would not.
你没有杀他
You did not kill him.
鬼子杀的而已
The enemy did.
不
No.
肯定是我害死他的 这点我很肯定
No, I killed him as surely as I'm now here.
他也是我们之间的一份子啊
And he was one of ours.
他罪有应得而已
It was right that he should die.
你会怪我吗
And will you hate me?
我为什么要怪你呢
Why would I hate you?
我这么瘦
I am so thin.
一身骨头
My flesh is so hard.
一副黄脸婆的样子
My face is dark and not like a woman's face.
你是跟刚结婚的时候不一样
You do not look as you did when I married you, it is true.
如果我当年也长成现在这样 你还会娶我吗
Would you have married me then if I had looked as I do now?
肯定 不会
Doubtless, I would not.
但是我也不是当年的我了啊
But I myself was not the same man that I am now.
那些东西 也不是我现在需要的
And what pleased me then would not please me now.
- 那我有你需要的东西吗  - 有
- Do I please you now? - You do.
一直都有 你对我的爱...
As always, this feeling between us...
始终不变
...we can return to it from anything.
夏天过去了
And then summer was gone.
谷物开始有收成了
And the grain had kept its promise.
两个老人再次等待着小玉跟他们的二儿子的归来
Again, the old ones waited for the return of Jade and her husband...
他们去参加游击队的集会
... who'd been summoned to the meeting place in the hills.
有人来了
Someone comes.
是孩子们回来了吧
It is our children, home from the hills.
- 你们回来了啊   - 爹娘
- Well, then, you are back. - Father, Mother.
- 你们都好吧  - 都很好
- You are well. - Well enough.
-你们刚好回来帮忙收割庄稼
You are in time to help us harvest.
如果我们够聪明 应该可以平安过冬
If we are clever, we can pass this winter safely.
今年庄稼长得好 谷粒都沉甸甸的
The crop is good this year and the grain lies heavy in the hand.
是啊
Yes.
这片土地养活过多少代人啊
This field would feed many people.
爹 你能召集一下村里的当家们吗
Father, will you call the heads of the village?
我们有任务需要他们去做
We have a task for them to do.
现在开会 现在天亮呢 太危险了
A meeting? But there is a danger in a meeting while it is still light.
告诉他们天一黑就集合
Tell them to gather at the first hour of the darkness.
有件事情我们必须马上去做
There is a thing we must do,and at once.
只要我们喂着鬼子 就打不倒他们
The enemy will never be defeated if we feed him...
但是如果没有我们的食物 他们就会饿死
...but without our food, he will starve.
- 我可不拆了我的房子 - 这太过分了
- I will not destroy food nor my house. - It's too much.
- 这样做没道理啊  - 这是指挥部要求的
- It's against the law of man to do it. - It is the task the high command has set.
你们必须把所有东西都烧掉
You must burn all you have and leave only the ashes behind you.
儿子啊 你怎么能要求相亲们做这种事情啊
Can it be that you, my son, ask this of me and our kinsmen?
我说的是我们必须消灭鬼子们
I ask it that the enemy may be destroyed.
我们现在不仅仅要喂饱他们 还得替他们干活
Not only do we feed them but we stay here as their work animals.
你们这些年轻人只会胡言乱语啊
What we hear are the words of a young fool.
我是不会听你们的话的
I, for one, will not listen to any more.
我不会抛下我的家的 也不会离开我的土地的
I will not burn my house,nor leave what I have.
我们可不可以 留下来一边抵抗
But we... We resist here.
一边偷偷藏东西吃呢
We keep what food we can from the enemy...
然后有机会我们再打死他们呢
...and we kill him how and when we can.
- 这就够了吧  - 还远远不够
- It is enough. - It is not enough.
- 你不爱你的国家吗 爹  - 爱国?
- Do you not love your country? - Love my country?
你来告诉我 我难道不爱脚下这片土地吗
You say that to me? Do I not love this earth and is this earth not my country?
我死了也要留下来保护它啊
Though I die, I stay with it.
这世界上还有没有一个人能像这样去爱护她的国家
Can a man love his country better than that?
但是 爹 这片土地
But, my father,this earth is only your country...
只有国家和平的时候才属于你啊
...in peacetime when there is freedom.
我不管 我会留下来守护这片土地
I know only this. We must hold the land.
你也就只会守着这一块破地了
You will hold only a handful of dead soil.
你这样做早晚连你的国家都没有了
You will lose your whole country doing it.
- 我不想听  - 老凌说的对
- I will not listen. - Ling Tan is right as always.
是的 我们也要留下来 守着这片土地
Yes, we will not leave our land. We will hold it.
奇怪了 今晚怎么所有人都拉长了脸啊
Now, what's wrong with all these long faces?
我们没有谈妥
We have failed.
爹跟乡亲们都拒绝了我们的建议
Our kinsmen and our father among them have refused our plan.
- 你们怎么能不按上级的指示去做呢  - 我不会 相亲们也不会
- You will not do as you're told to do? - I will not, nor will the other kinsmen.
那就没办法了 现在只能用枪逼他们同意了
There's an answer. Hold a gun at their heads and make them do it.
- 还是得经过他们的同意才好啊  - 那些老不死的是不会同意的
- It must be their own will. - The old should be allowed no will.
又是什么老人年轻人这种说法 再开几次会不就好了嘛
The old and the new again. There must be some meeting.
开什么会 让这帮老不死的跟我们这些活人开会
There's no meeting what is dead and what is alive.
爹跟这些人一样都太老顽固了 活腻了
Father and men like him grow too old and have walked too long.
该是我们年轻人当家做主的时候了
Others need the room they take.
你竟然敢打我
You may not strike me.
我就是要打你
I should beat you.
你现在只知道杀人 你个嗜血的畜生
Killing and love of killing, that is all you know.
是的 但是我很清楚 现在时代不同了
Yes, but I know it well. These are other times.
我也可以像杀死别人一样杀了你
And I can kill you as well as any other.
那是肯定 你可以杀了我
Yes, you can kill me.
你现在谁都可以杀了
I think you can kill anyone now.
但是我已经不想再杀人了
But I will kill no more.
- 你回来啊  - 我不会再回来这个家了
- Come back here. - I will not.
我受够了这个愚蠢的家了 今天是最后一次了
I've eaten enough foolishness in this house, and for the last time.
我得跟着他
I must go with him.
你们可以来游击队那里找我们 如果你们愿意来的话
You will find us in the hills,for you will follow us.
这个家完了
Happiness in this family is over.
没什么值得留恋的东西了
Nothing is left to anyone...
如果长辈都不能让晚辈听话的话
...if the old can no longer look to the young for obedience.
我这么说吧
I have come to this.
如果以后有人告诉我老三死了 我是不会掉一滴眼泪的
I will not grieve the day they tell me my third son is dead.
他已经变成了我最痛恨 最可怕的哪种人了
He has become the sort of man I hate and fear most.
这种人不会过安稳日子的
Such men will not allow peace in the world.
他们一碰到战争 就像干柴烈火一样
War springs from them as fire does from tinder...
好像这就是他们的人生乐趣
...and is their pleasure in their life.
这种人死了更好
Such men should die for the good of all.
你这是在指责你儿子的理想啊
You blame your son for what he is.
那我应该指责谁呢
Who should I blame, then?
他亲口反抗我 他是个不孝子啊
It was his own arm he raised against me and his own voice.
你不应该怪他的 爹
You cannot blame him.
他的生活都没有正常过
Has his life been as it should?
他有过安稳日子好去娶个老婆吗
Has he had peace to live and find a wife?
他有时间去生个小孩吗
Have sons of his own?
他把所有的时间都用在了一件事情上
No, he put the will he would have used...
整天打打杀杀
...into another thing: The will to kill.
从他看了第一次杀人之后 整个人就都变了
So changed from the boy who wretched at the sight of the first dead...
变得连自己的亲生父亲都打
...that he would strike his own father.
我们不也是变了很多吗
Well, are we not all changed?
如果不把鬼子赶出去 我们还能变回来吗
Can we get our old selves back if the devils are not driven out soon?
你可以吗
Can you?
你...
You...
你也能杀鬼子
You hate to kill above all else.
你杀过鬼子
Yet you have killed...
- 你比其他人都能杀鬼子  - 我不听
-  ...as skillfully as you once tilled the land. - I will not hear this.
你应该听听 你看娘 难道她就没变
But you shall hear it. And our mother, has she not changed?
她以前见到鬼子就跑 现在抡起锄头
Now she runs, takes up her hoe and buries the enemy...
迎头就能抡掉一个鬼子
...as though the human flesh were animal.
她还能变回去吗 她能忘了这些发生过的事情吗
Can she get back to the old way? Can she forget what she's done?
还有你的儿子们 个个都会杀人 你的三儿子更是个嗜血杀人狂
And your sons, they all kill. Your third son because he has come to love it.
你大儿子不是也因为觉得杀人轻而易举吗 而我老公
Your eldest because it's the easiest thing to do and my...
是因为他必须这么做 我们都杀人狂
Your second son because he must.But we all kill.
我们杀来杀去 你能否认这些事情吗
We kill and kill again. Can you deny this?
不 不 我不能
No, no, I cannot.
我自己都学会前面开完枪
I've learned to hold a gun and fire it from the doorway.
后门就回来喂儿子了
And then go in and feed my son.
你看看你孙子 吃的都是什么啊
And what is the child eat into himself with the food?
你瞧瞧 你仔细瞧瞧
Look at him. Look at him.
别转过去 看这里
Do not turn away.
即使你孙子都开始用牙齿磨弹壳了
Even now your grandchild sharpens his little teeth on an empty shell...
他都不怕火药味的
...and does not hate the taste of gunpowder.
他还小 也没什么思想
He's young still. His mind, at least, is untouched.
他还有救 还可以过正常人的生活
He can be saved and taught a decent way to live...
除非鬼子被我们赶出这个国家
...if the enemy is driven from our country.
如果这种战争的恐惧继续的话 他会变成什么
What will become of him if this horror goes on?
我应该怎么教会她城市 如果所有人都互相欺骗
How can I teach him honesty when he must lie and cheat to live?
我又怎么教会他仁慈 如果所有人都拼个你死我活
How can I teach him mercy when he must either kill first or be killed?
我如何叫他相信别人...
How can I teach him faith in mankind...
但他看到家里充满了不信任跟背叛呢
...when he sees nothing but distrust and when even in his own family are traitors.
- 难道我应该为此负责吗  - 你不用负责
- Am I to blame for these things? - You're not.
但是你有责任 我们都有责任
But you will be to blame, we'll all be to blame...
除非我们把鬼子们赶出我们国家...
...unless we defeat the Japanese and drive them from this country...
而且不让他们再次侵略我们
...and prevent them from ever doing this again.
如果你孩子问你为什么放弃这片土地 你该跟他如何解释呢
How will you answer your son when he asks you why you left our land?
我会告诉他...
I will tell him...
我会告诉他 我们这样做救了他跟全家
I will tell him it was to save him and his family...
还有整个国家
...and his whole country.
你没有...
You had no...
我不能这么做
I cannot...
我还是没想通.
For a cloud covers my mind.
老二 你现在作何打算
What will you do now, my son?
我们要加入游击队 至少我们可以跟鬼子继续斗下去
We will join our brothers in the hills where at least we can fight on.
天亮前我们就必须离家出发
We will leave this house during the last hours of the darkness before dawn.
这些是给你们路上吃的
Here is food for your journey.
你能来我们感激不尽
We are glad you have come.
我知道对你很不容易,
It would have been a bitter thing if you had not.
如果你们愿意等 我们跟你们一起走
If you can wait, we will go with you.
跟我们一起
Go with us?
是的 我会烧掉房子跟田地 跟你们一起走
Yes, I will burn my fields and my house and go with you.
我耳朵聋了吧 老头子?
Do my ears hear what you are saying, old man?
我们应当这么做 我心里没有顾虑了
They hear what we must do, for the cloud is now gone from my mind.
我已经跟乡亲们说过了
I have spoken to all our kinsmen in the village...
告诉他们你昨晚说的事情
...and told them the things you told me.
我给他们时间考虑 但是我会先烧掉我的房子
I gave them the hour that I would fire my house...
然后让他们也烧掉自己的房子
..and asked them to do the same thing.
- 他们会吗  - 现在我不清楚
- But will they? - I do not know.
说服他们不容易 这不是他们的本性
It is a great deal to ask of them, and against their natures.
但是我跟我儿子怎么办
But what will become of me and my children?
带上他们去山里找老大去
You will go and take your children to where my sons are in the hills.
- 老沈家的儿子会照顾好大姐的  - 好 那我们去那里会合
- The son of Neighbor Shen can guide her. - Yes. We will meet you there.
你也带上我们儿子
And you will take our son too.
留点记号在这里
These things will mark our land...
说不定我们回来了还能找到这片地方
...so when we come back we can prove it is ours and claim it.
那是什么玩意啊
What nonsense is this?
一会这里全变成灰了 你现在瞎弄什么东西啊
In a while, these things will be ashes, so, what matter how they look now?
人死之前 是不是得有人帮忙料理一下后事啊
Would you bury a friend without first arranging him decently?
在这个屋子里面 你爹 你爷爷都住在这里
In these rooms, your father and his father before him died.
你的儿子也是在这里出生 按理也应该在这里终老的
And our children were born here and should die here.
我帮过你一次了 这次你来帮我挖洞
I helped you dig once, now you help me.
- 不过我还是有点担心  - 担心啥
- A worry has struck me. - What now, woman?
如果上次说的那个地里头另一边的陌生人 闯进来了
What if the stranger who walks on the other side of your land...
找到这些东西偷走了怎么办
...finds these things and steals them?
- 他不会偷我们的  - 你怎么知道
- He will not steal from us. - How can you know that?
我头一遭想得这么清楚啦
I see clearly now, and for the first time.
三表哥说了世界上只有一个太阳跟月亮
Third cousin once said that there is one sun and one moon for all.
如果这个是对的 大家都共用一个月亮跟太阳
If that is true, all share the sun and moon...
那我们为什么不共用一片土地呢
...why should we not also all share the earth?
这个村子只是这个世界的一小角落而已
This valley is not the world but only part of the world.
还有很多像我一样没见过世面的人
And there are others like me whose faces I have never seen.
而且 人们都是爱好和平的啊
Elsewhere, there are men who love peace...
他们心地善良 为了和平而战斗
...and long for good and who will fight to get these things.
这样一说 陌生人就不陌生 而是和我一模一样的人
So the stranger is no longer a stranger to me but a man like me.
要是我能认识他那该多好
If I could but know him.
要是我能看到他那该多好
If I could but see him.
但是你们语言不通怎么一起说话呢
What good to see him
if you could not speak?
你不用说
You would not need speech.
如果理想一样 就能彼此理解
If what you wish is the same, there would be understanding between you.
对的对的 是这样说的
Yes, that is true.
不知为什么 今晚我感觉到有股力量横扫全世界
Somehow tonight, I feel that there is a power sweeping around the world...
将全世界的陌生人都联合到了一起
...bringing us all together with that stranger.
- 我也感觉到了 爹  - 我也是
- And I, too, feel it, my father. - So do I.
- 我怎么感觉不到呢  - 到时间了爹
- Why am I left out of this?  - It is time now, my father.
- 我来点火吗 - 不
- Shall I fire the house? - No.
我跟你娘来
Your mother and I will do this.
我们先去烧掉东边的地
We will fire the east field first, then.
北边的最后再烧 这样我们可以从那里走出去
Leave the north fields for the last,so that we may escape that way.
老太婆 再多看一眼
Look back once, old woman.
以后就再也看不着了
Then look back no more.
沿着山路走
Keep to the hill road.
爹 快看
My father, look.
会不会是有个乡亲跟着我们呢
Can it be even one of our kinsmen is with us?
好像只是个灯笼
It is only a lantern.
不是不是 那是火
No. No, it is a fire.
- 还有还有  - 那边也点着了
- And there's another. - And another.
-不会吧 整个村子都点着了 -是的 老太婆 我们不是孤零零的一家子
- Can it be? The whole village? - It is, old woman. We are not alone.
- 我走不动了 老头子  - 你上次是不是还没有被打舒服
- I'm weary, my lord. - But you are not bruised as yet.
你怎么不跟我们一起走
Why can you not come with us?
不 娘 我和我弟弟们属于这里
No, my mother. My place is here with my brothers.
敌人不敢来这里的 娘 大姐会平安无事 还会有饭吃的
The enemy fears to come here. My sister will be safe and have food.
这样最好 前面的路会很难走的 老太婆 我们女儿她....
I think it best. Our road ahead will be hard, old woman. And our daughter...
爹 我看到你们做的事情了 我也看到乡亲们所做的牺牲了
My father, I have seen what you have done, and the others also.
我感到很惭愧
I am ashamed.
我更惭愧 我的儿子啊
No more than I, my son.
我现在真正觉得你才是
Well, then, I would have you take your place of command...
真正的一家之主
...as head of our family once more.
我知道另外一个更重要的事情 比一家之主还重要
I think there is now another command,even above that.
我们都知道我们应该去做些什么 而且我们也会去做
We have each been told what we must do, and we will do it.
- 你们年轻人留下来跟鬼子打仗  - 那你呢 爹
- You that our young will stay here and fight. - And you, Father?
我得去给这双老手找一个用得上它们的地方
I would be where these hands can be used.
我打算跟你娘去解放区
I and my old woman will go into free China...
好给你们这些打仗的年轻人种点吃
...and raise food to fill your bellies while you fight.
那我们就出发了 趁着现在还有力气
Let us go, then, while the strength is still in us.
还有一件事情
There is a thing.
如果我们有人活着回来 记得回来 认领我们的地
If one of us lives, he must go back one day to claim the land.
我就这么吩咐你们了
I so charge you all.
如果你们还活着 就应该回来看看
If you live, you must do this.
我们陪你走一段 爹
My wife and I will walk a little way with you.
我们去送送你们
We would see you out of sight.
今天我们虽然要分离了 但是感觉比以前都要亲近
At this moment we part,we are closer than ever before.
这小家伙什么时候开始念书啊
When will this one begin to read?
越快越好
As soon as he can be taught.
他会学得很快的 他可是我们未来的希望啊
He will learn quickly, for he is the hope of us all.
他的眼睛 雪亮着呢
His eyes are open.
教他念书的老师 眼睛也应该这么雪亮
Make sure that the one who teaches him has his eyes open also.
我们会找到这样的老师的 我们刚找到他们
We will do that. We do it now.
带上你的孙子吧 爹
Take your grandchild with you.
是的 爹 带上他
Yes, my father, take him with you.
好好照顾他 教导他
Care for him and teach him.
他会跟我亲生的一样的
He will be as our own.
他本来就是你的亲生孙子啊
What else? For that is what he is.
于是老凌头把土地甩在脑后
So it came about that while Ling Tan left the land behind him...
他并没有失去希望
... he did not leave hope.
他把希望寄托在未来的一代 小玉的孩子身上
For he carried it with him in Jade's child.
这个小孩才是真正的龙种
That child so truly,the seed of the dragon.